<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Catechisme for communicants. Set forth for the benefit of the willing to be well prepared for the receiving of that great mystery of the Lords Supper. / By A wel-willer [sic] unto all the children and servants in this great citie, and the suburbs, but most especially those of the parish of Dunstans East, London.</title>
            <author>Bridges, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77379</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4483C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504350</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504350</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171649</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77379)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171649)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2583:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Catechisme for communicants. Set forth for the benefit of the willing to be well prepared for the receiving of that great mystery of the Lords Supper. / By A wel-willer [sic] unto all the children and servants in this great citie, and the suburbs, but most especially those of the parish of Dunstans East, London.</title>
                  <author>Bridges, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 103 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.C. for Andrew Crook, at the Green Dragon in Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle" signed: Walter Bridges.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171649:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CATECHISME FOR COMMVNICANTS.</p>
            <p>Set forth for the benefit of the willing to be well prepared for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of that great Myſtery of the LORDS SVPPER.</p>
            <p>By a Wel-willer unto all the children and ſervants in this great Cities, and the Suburbs, but moſt eſpecially thoſe of the Pariſh of <hi>Dunſtans Eaſt London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Sicut ſpeculum pulchrum in Fabrica aurea, in Domo caecipoſitum, Sicut lyra ſurdo, ſic favus in ore mortui leonis, ſic Sacramentum non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus, non praeparatis, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>The Lord our God made a breach at firſt upon you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſought him not in due order,</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> Chro. <hi>15.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>I am come to do ſacrifice to the Lord, ſanctifie your ſelves, and come with me to the ſacrifice,</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>16.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>R. C.</hi> for <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> at the Green Dragon in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171649:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171649:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right worſhipfull, and others the inhabitants of the Pariſh of <hi>Dunſtans Eaſt</hi> LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you and I, and all that love light, bad ever cauſe to bleſſe God for the ſame, let us now begin to thinke of our dutie: none of our leaſt thankes ſurely is due for the Catechiſme; Candles lighted and burning bright, one after another, and all from the great Torch of Gods holy Word. The dimneſſe (to my knowledge) is yet very great, yea even here where ſo many fired Beacons now burne out. Now becauſe ſome, perhaps, will read ſuch a Catechiſme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a one writ it, though for nothing elſe; I have adventured to ſet on fire this little Candle alſo. Some lights I know are of Tallow, and pleaſant enough for light, but the ſent unſavorie, this is wax, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered with ſome diligence too, and if it may make any heart like melting wax as <hi>David</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:171649:3"/>ſpeakes, <hi>Pſal. 22.14.</hi> or become a Taper ſerving for a light to feet and a Lanthorne to pathes; as every thing of truth gathered out of Gods Word ought to doe, it will bee well for you, and for mee not amiſſe, your integrity ſhall ſurely redound upon your own heads, and if (I helpe you) ſome of your wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing ſhall bee put on mine accompt. All knowledge doth, and indeed ought to tend to practiſe, but catechiſticall knowledge, moſt eſpecially, concerning which, <hi>Exod. 12.26.</hi> And ſuch knowledge in theſe (ſeeming knowing, but indeed) ignorant times, is I beleeve, the beſt Pilot, guide, and uſher, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to godly practiſe; Divinitie propounds three noble ends unto her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>1.</hi> is Gods glory, the higheſt and moſt ſupreame.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Is mans ſanctification here, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation hereafter.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Is the edification and converſion of our neighbours, and thoſe that relate unto us; to all theſe ends ſuch knowledge, as is drawne from catechiſticall principles, looks directly.
<note place="margin">Wolphius.</note> Hee ſaid ſweetly, God gave not man his Lawes to preſerve onely; for then he might have committed them to iron Cheſts or marble Pillars: nor onely to talke of them; for then hee might have given them
<pb facs="tcp:171649:3"/>to Geeſe or Parrats: nor yet onely for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation; for then the Owles in Ivy woods, or the Monks in Cloyſters had beene fitteſt to have received them; Gods purpoſe was and ſtill is, not to make tryall of the wits of men who could ſharplieſt conceive, nor of their memories who could faithfullieſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, nor of their eloquence who could round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt diſcourſe, but of their wills who would moſt obediently doe that which hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them. Theſe directions (Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) intend your practiſe onely, and as in all things, ſo eſpecially, in your approches unto God in his moſt holy things; that his Table be not made a ſnare unto you. One Apple of the tree of life is better then ten of the tree of the knowledge of good and evill; though wee, in our longings, fondly preferre theſe before the other, ever ſince our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents teeth were ſet on edge therewithall. Some of the maine heads of Divinity are here handled, as our miſery and our mercy;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nazian: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Syſt. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. p.</hi> 212.</note> our diſeaſe and the cure, as hee ſaid well, The remedy you have here, in the meanes preſcribed, to the Fall in the effects; <hi>I</hi> pray you ſtill remember, that the purpoſe of all is for, and the profit will be found in practiſe, that as hee ſaid excellently, The Faith of the eares and that of the hands may goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb facs="tcp:171649:4"/>I finde of old foure great complaints,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Ruffin. Eccl. hiſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Moſes Lucio, Arr. Epiſcop.</hi>
               </note> (by no ſmall men neither) fitted for their ſeverall times, but indeed, too too ſuitable unto ours alſo. The firſt <hi>(Seneca)</hi> ſaies <hi>Malint diſputare quam vivere,</hi> Men had rather fall to diſputing downe one another, then endeavour to live up to God: too true, God wot. The ſecond ſaith, men know, onely that they may bee knowne by it, <hi>Sciunt ut ſciantur, Bernard.</hi> The third ſaies of the Athenians thus, <hi>Nummis ad nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum, et ſcientia ad ſciendum utun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> They uſe their money to count withall, and their knowledge to know withall. And the fourth ſaith of the Philoſophers of his time,
<note place="margin">Cum Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophorum vita, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiliter pugnat ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Tully.</note> That their lives and their diſcourſes did moſt miſerably croſſe one another. Such as any of theſe I would by no meanes have, either you or my ſelfe to bee, but active, and doing Chriſtians; in this, much of light, leſt peradventure, that of our Lord, <hi>Joh. 15.22.</hi> or that Joh. <hi>9.41.</hi> bee applyed unto us unavoidably. Indeed I muſt needs tell you Gentlemen that though few in theſe times bee troubled with deafe and dumbe ſpirits, yet abundance have withered hands, and dryed armes, and lame feet. The blood (under the Law) was appointed to bee put upon the lap of the right eare,
<pb facs="tcp:171649:4"/>the top of the right thumbe, and upon the toe of the right foot, you know, and why ſo? That the hearing, practiſe, and progreſſe of Gods people might bee ſanctified: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed then are wee like to prevaile with God, and to prepare men for him,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Theo. in Iud.</note> when like <hi>Gideons</hi> Souldiers wee beare in the one hand the Trumpet of preaching, piety, profeſſion, and in the other the burning lampe of Godly converſation. And yee Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Maſters of Families ſuffer a little I pray you the word of exhortation; Let not all theſe Catechiſmes riſe up in judgement againſt you, whilſt either you or yours continue uninſtructed, and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſably ſo (as you muſt needs bee) in theſe times,
<note place="margin">Miſerrimi omninum illi ſunt, qui fidem in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Fidei non habent. Cypr. De mortalitate.</note> unbeleevers (as the Father) in Faiths houſe, and groſſely ignorant, under all meanes of knowledge; The condemnation you know what it is, <hi>Joh. 3.19.</hi> And I know on whom it will lie, if it bee not prevented, even on you in this Citie, and yours too; One I remember brings Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in complayning of their relations thus, Alas!
<note place="margin">Perdidit nos aliena perfidia, parentes ſenſimus parricidas.</note> other mens untruſtineſſe hath undone us; wee have found our parents our overthrowers; I beſeech you in the bowels of the Lord Jeſus, bee not content to runne altogether after your earthly buſineſſe, but
<pb facs="tcp:171649:5"/>mind a little the one thing neceſſary. <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> tels us of a certaine carnall Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
<note place="margin">He calls him <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clops Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliophorus</hi> in his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of a carnal Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peller.</note> who carried on one ſide a bottle of rich Sack, and on the other the New Teſtament of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> Tranſlation, fairely bound and boſſed, with gilt leaves as faire as his life was foule, and his conditions baſe. Hee carried it alwayes about him, that was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and once had knocked it about the pate of a Franciſcan, for rayling againſt <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and the new Goſpellers. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the man hee is asked, what if hee were tied ever to carry the bottle at his girdle, and never to taſte of it, or if to taſte onely, and never drinke it down; his anſwer is, That were a puniſhment juſt <hi>Tantalus</hi> like; but what if hee did (as his manner was) drink deeply thereof? Hee then anſwers, it would warme his heart, refreſh his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and cheere his countenance; So, oh ſo, ſaith hee that ſpake to him, would that little booke thy ſoule, if thou didſt eate it downe, concoct, digeſt, and turne into nutriment, in thy life and practiſe. I know you will ſoone apply this; taſte a little, and ſee how excellent it is to bee able to ſerve the Lord, and ſave your owne ſoules. You have here two things in generall which are dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at for your direction.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171649:5"/>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Why you ought to let your profiting ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to all men in this knowledge, namely, becauſe wee are all moſt miſerable by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and have to doe with a moſt mercifull God, who had thoughts of our recovery from everlaſting by free grace.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> What is to be done of thoſe, that this may come to paſſe in their ſoules? <hi>viz.</hi> To have a moſt eſpeciall regard unto the holy uſe of, and wholeſome profit by the Word and Sacraments. The Maximes and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of things to bee done and beleeved, are very few, and contained in briefe Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maries; but the incentives, motives, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, reproofes and ſuch like things, for practiſe, theſe make volumes ſwell, theſe leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Sermons, and multiply bookes of all ſorts. Surely the ſinnes amongſt us in theſe times, do not proceed from ignorance all, but many of them from incontinence; ſome from the deſpiſing of knowledge; others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men with-hold the truth in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and not a few from that. That ſo many things are in deſpute, and ſo few in practiſe; Great lights burne and give light, tis true: But hold forth ſo many queſtions, that many, yea moſt men, will not bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to read or attend the anſwers. A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man there was, not far from this place, and
<pb facs="tcp:171649:6"/>lately living in a profeſſed doubt of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; after illumination and repentance, ſhee very hardly received comfort. Now ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed often that the vitious and offenſive life of a great learned man in the towne where ſhee lived, occaſioned thoſe damnable doubts; If a ſtranger ſhould come here and ſee our books, heare our Sermons, view our Miniſtery, and but a little attend unto the tatling part of our windy profeſſours, which are all tongue, hee would ſurely think our Theory to bee unparalleled, and our Land and Citie in ſpeciall to bee knowing of all things which are knowable. But if hee ſhould goe into many families, and ſee them at home, if hee ſhould view our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs a little, and but make a ſtep into the Villages round about <hi>London;</hi> if hee ſhould walke our ſtreets and heare our Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Carmen, &amp;c. their oathes, idle, yea and evill ſpeaking, verily the ingenuous Traveller would ſay of this Citie, as once was ſaid of one greater then it, Here are <hi>600000.</hi> which know not their right hand from the left; notwithſtanding both Preſſe and Pulpit doe ſo abound with knowledge, and the labours of learned men; for the ſakes of theſe, and ſuch as theſe, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and willing to know, your children
<pb facs="tcp:171649:6"/>and ſervants I have drawne theſe Sermon notes into a way of Catechiſme, and doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat that they will, not onely find leaſure, but make ſome opportunitie to read and practiſe.
<note place="margin">Socrates.</note> The great learned man was wont to ſay, that hee that would bee an honeſt man, ſhall ſoone bee ſo, and is indeed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſt the hardeſt part of the worke; not much unlike to what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, Wiſedome is eaſie to him that will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.
<note place="margin">Linacer.</note> It is ſaid of one that reading the <hi>5.6.</hi> and <hi>7.</hi> Chapters of <hi>St. Matthew,</hi> hee began to compare thoſe rules preſently to his owne and unto other Chriſtians lives alſo, and when hee had ſo done, throwes downe the booke, and ſaies, Either this is not Gods Goſpell, or elſe wee are not Chriſtians and Goſpellers; holy application, Gentlemen, will bring forth holy indignation; holy indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation I ſay, ſuch as, <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>7.11.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with ſome rules of direction for the uſe of this and ſuch like better workes. Firſt, to Catechize is to teach the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, See <hi>Heb. 5.12.</hi> and <hi>6.1.</hi> and is uſed in Scripture to traine up, as Children and Servants ought to bee, <hi>Prov. 22.6.</hi> to inſtruct, <hi>Luk. 1.4.</hi> It is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Miniſter, <hi>Ezek. 44.23.</hi> But not of him onely, as too many thinke, ſee
<pb facs="tcp:171649:7"/>
               <hi>Deut. 4.10.</hi> and <hi>Deut. 6.6, 7.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, take heed I pray you of two deſtructive principles, one of the Courtier, Religion he ſaies muſt not goe too high, <hi>Amos 7.13.</hi> Prophecy no more at <hi>Bethel,</hi> for it is the Kings houſe; the other of the Countreyman and Citizen too, Let not Religion goe too low, what need wee teach it our children or our ſervants? See <hi>Pſal. 34.11.</hi> and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſuch words for ever; <hi>1.</hi> The dutie is, children to bee taught; <hi>2.</hi> The manner of their teaching, to bee by way of Catechiſe. <hi>3.</hi> What they to bee Catechized are to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, that is, to come and hearken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, obſerve well what is the cauſe of the want of publike profit to your children and ſervants at Church, even their rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and unpreparedneſſe at home: you ſend them to ſchoole, and prepare them for mens ſervice, but they come to Gods ſervice ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant utterly of the goodneſſe and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof, come to Church without prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and goe away without profit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Countryman went to the Phyſitian for Phyſick, to whom the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian gave a bill, which the patient put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his pocket ſafe, and wore it there a great
<pb facs="tcp:171649:7"/>while, but finding no eaſe of his trouble comes againe, and the Phyſitian bids him take it in Poſſet Ale, hee goes home and puts the bill into the cup, but never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the ingredients preſcribed to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his body. Now looke how much good his Phyſick did him; juſt ſo much will Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie doe you, unleſſe you let ſuch words as theſe ſinke downe into your eares, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you receive the Word with readineſſe, and ſearch the Scriptures whether theſe things bee ſo, that many of you (and yours) may beleeve, ſee <hi>Act. 17.11, 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly and laſtly, mens Catechiſes are all nothing unleſſe you bee alſo taught of God, therefore weigh well the promiſe, <hi>Act. 2.17.</hi> and bee ſure you cleave cloſe to the performance hee requires of every graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man. If you looke into <hi>Heb. 1.2.</hi> Chriſt is ſaid to bee heire of all things; then look into <hi>Pſal. 2.8.</hi> and there God ſaith, <hi>Aske of mee, and I will give thee the heathen for thine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp;c.</hi> You may conclude hence that what God meanes to give to his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sonne, hee yet meanes hee ſhall aske him; How much more doth bee require of his adopted ones? Therefore, <hi>Epheſ. 6.18,
<pb facs="tcp:171649:8"/>19. Brethren, pray alwayes, with all manner of ſupplications in the Spirit, and watch thereunto with all perſeverance, and ſupplication, for all Saints: and for mee</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant in the Goſpel, and a ſuiter at the Throne of Grace for you all <hi>Walter Bridges.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Minchin Lane, <date>Novem. <hi>23. 1645.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171649:8"/>
            <head>A CATECHISME for Communicants.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> God is a Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24. and ſuch a Spirit as hath life in himſelfe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. What doe you thinke concerning the holy Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That there is a Trinitie of Perſons I undoubtedly beleeve, namely God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture telleth mee ſo plainely, as in many other, ſo in theſe places, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.26.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But I beare ſome Divines expreſſing themſelves in ſtrange tearmes, Trinity, unity, eſſentiall, coeſſentiall, &amp;c. how ſhall plaine people underſtand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are grounded on the holy Scripture,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171649:9"/>for example, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. There are three and theſe three are one, a Trinitie in unitie. Eſſence of God meaneth the being of God, ſhewed in the Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14. I am, and <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. hee was, is, and is to come. Coeſſentiall meaneth one being together with another, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.10. For the being or eſſence of God is conſidered either without diſtinction as it is perfectly in God himſelfe, or with diſtinction with reſpect to the Perſons in Trinity, abſolutely or relatively, ſo is the expreſſion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ought I diſtinctly to beleeve concerning God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Theſe two things; firſt, That God is onely one, in power, nature, eſſence, deitie. Secondly, that there are three perſons, Father, Sonne and holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where doe you prove that theſe three Perſons bee all of them God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Sonne is proved to be God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. the holy Ghoſt proved to bee God, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3. lied unto the holy Ghoſt, and <hi>ver.</hi> 4. thou haſt not lied unto man but unto God. The Father to bee God who doubteth?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where doe you prove that theſe three are one God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that before mentioned, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. And theſe three are one.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſimilitude would you uſe to make this plaine by?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171649:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By this: the Sun hath three things in it, heat, light, and motion; every one of theſe is ſeparate from other, and yet all together make up one Sunne, the heat is not the light, neither is that the motion: ſo in the Trinity; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not the Sonne, nor the holy Ghoſt, but the Father, Sonne and holy Ghoſt make up one God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What ſimilitude would you expreſſe the being in God by?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By the very ſame: As in the Sunnes light there are degrees, Morning, Noone, Twilight, and yet all make but one light: or as in the heat of the Sunne, there are degrees too, and yet all make but one heat; ſo the perſons of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or diverſe manners of being in God, do not multiply the divine eſſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſumme of that then which you thinke meet for private people to learne concerning the Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The eſſence or being of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4. The manner of being in three perſons, as is ſaid before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What more ſhould I underſtand concerning the Trinitie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That there is ſomething common to all the three perſons of the Trinitie, as the Godhead, power, and nature, and ſo the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt are God.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171649:10"/>
            <p>There is ſomething proper to them alſo, as the ſeverall properties of the three Perſons; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, it is proper to the Father to beget, to the Sonne to be begotten, and to the holy Ghoſt to proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What ſhort expreſſion would you uſe, to expreſſe the Trinitie by to a man which you would have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Such as this:</p>
            <p n="1">1. God the Father is God underſtanding.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God the Sonne is God underſtood.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God the holy Ghoſt is God loved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What workes of the Trinitie am I to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard unto, in every ſever all Perſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Theſe: 1. The Creation, which is the Fathers worke, and that of government too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Redemption, which is the work of the Sonne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The application or ſanctification, which is the worke of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>All which a Chriſtian is to raiſe his affection with all that hee may bee the better ſtirred up to the due praiſe of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. In what eſtate is all mankind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In a very ſad, becauſe ſinfull, eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But why was our eſtate of innocency mutable? and why was man left to fall? and to a changeable eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. That God may bee knowne to bee the onely immutable one; ſee the Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171649:10"/>
               <hi>James</hi> 1.17. <hi>I am God, I change not, Mal.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That God may bee juſt in puniſhing ſinne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That a way may be made to the ſalvation of a loſt world, wherein God had appointed to ſhew himſelfe as juſt and mercifull in our recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as wee had ſhewed our ſelves unjuſt and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in our fall. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. How long ſtood men and Angels in their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of innocency?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Wee cannot tell, but certainly they ſtood ſo but a very ſhort time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Was there a condition annexed to this eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yes, and it was this: So long as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue holy by obeying my word, ſo long onely you ſhall bee happy by injoying my preſence. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.16.17. with <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But what were the cauſes of, and the manner of mans fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> God certainly neither commanded nor yet counſelled it: Let all bee expreſſed to you (to avoid tediouſneſſe) by this ſimilitude: a wiſe father purpoſing to let his ſonne ſee his owne wilfulneſſe and intemperancy, together with his love and fatherly affection toward him, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth with himſelfe to make him fall into ſome mortall ſickneſſe, out of the which hee knoweth himſelfe to bee able to recover him: this hee will effect, not by giving him poyſon to drinke, for then hee ſhould bee the cauſe and juſtly beare the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171649:11"/>blame of that evill, but by laying it in his way, as it were a bait, in ſome ſweet meat, which hee knoweth that his Sonne loveth, and will eate as ſoone as hee feeleth it. And leſt hee ſhould plead ignorance, and ſo avoyd the blame of wilfulneſſe, the father forewarneth him of that kind of meat, charging him very inſtantly to abſtaine from it, as being unwholeſome, and hurtfull unto him, yet he doth not tell him what hee intendeth. This young man comming where this pleaſant meat is, remembreth his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers counſell and commandement, yet is by the entiſement of evill companions, and his owne appetite moved to eate of it, perſwading him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that there is no ſuch danger in it as his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would make him beleeve, and therefore no cauſe hee ſhould obey him in that matter. So hee eateth of it and poyſoneth himſelfe. Now no man will deny, but that both the father and the ſonne have a hand in this, yet not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who giveth the occaſion onely, but the young man himſelfe who doth willingly, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wilfully, take that hurtfull meat, is to bee blamed, and counted the cauſe of this evill. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. and apply this to the fall of mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But who can bee perſwaded to thinke, that Adam in the ſtate of his innocency eſpecially, could bee deceived with ſuch a thing as an Apple?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That which the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171649:11"/>muſt carefully bee, firſt marked, and ſecondly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, for <hi>Adam</hi> was not deceived, (that is not ſo ſoone, or not ſo throughly) but the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was in the tranſgreſſion. And as for the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> there was in it more of wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe then of blindneſſe, and indeed hee will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſobey God then diſpleaſe his wife. Thus of the fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What did man loſe in the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Two things; 1. The puritie of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, inherent; and what hee loſt, hee loſt not onely for himſelfe but for his poſteritie alſo: See <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. For as if treaſon bee committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a King, wee know it taints and defiles the blood and poſteritie alſo, ſo in treaſon ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all againſt the King of Kings it is; See <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The juſtice of his perſon alſo, for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is plaine, That whoſoever ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet faileth in one point, hee is guilty of all, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But how loſt hee theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It was not by any worke of God, but, as it is ſaid before, by a worke of his owne, and ſuch a work of himſelfe, as was not out of a wilfull deſire of renouncing God and all holineſſe, but ſurely it was,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the craft of Satan that old Serpent, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:171649:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. By the nature of ſinne, expreſſed in the Word of God to bee like leaven, which leavens the whole lump, and like a fretting canker; See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. With what ſucceſſe or event?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Alas! a moſt fearfull one, that is to ſay, originall ſinne came, and like a deluge overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both him and all his, ſo that now in ſinne wee are all borne and in iniquitie our mothers bring us forth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6. the iſſue whereof is, that wee neither doe nor can, know or beleeve, love or feare, obey or honour God as we ought to doe; nay more, the effect of our fall from God is a ſeparation from God, fraught with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and deformitie, and what not that is evill? See <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>tot.</hi> So much of the effect of the fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But how is this made viſible and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly plaine unto us? if a man fall into povertie, his rags, craving of almes, yea his very lookes doe ſhew it; if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſickneſſe, there are ſignes thereof: ſo of madneſſe, or any ſuch corporall perplexitie; but how is the ſpirituall miſery in the fall of mankind made plaine and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thus it is made plaine and eaſie to every one that is able and willing to ſee. That ſoule that was before holy, excellent, illuminate, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, is now quite contrary and repleat top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full with thoſe ſinnes in their viſibility, whereof
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171649:12"/>you have here a particular enumeration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Infidelitie;</p>
            <p>Of which wee have two remarkable inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or examples in holy Scripture of the firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers, Devils in their, and <hi>Adam</hi> in his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie: both whoſe ſinnes were in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler alike, to truſt in ſomething beſide God for their happineſſe: <hi>Adam</hi> truſts the Devill, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and the apple, and the Devill ſeeing no creature more excellent then himſelfe, thought it beſt to truſt himſelfe for his happineſſe too. And this ſinne is ordinarily practiſed, and ſo common that the Lord ſheweth us the very markes of our miſery every day therein.</p>
            <p>For victory, men truſt the Arme of fleſh; for health, the Phyſitian; for life, the neceſſaries of life, meate, drinke, &amp;c. for wealth, our owne induſtry, or that of our parents; for honour and glory, Kings and great ones in our preferment.</p>
            <p>Hence comes it to paſſe that the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſtate of the godly and renewed in this world is no leſſe then thus big, the godly have an affiance in God, the ungodly a defiance of God, which is a ſad difference. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>Job</hi> 21.14, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Deſperation</p>
            <p>Is another ſinne, which is viſible in man after
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171649:13"/>the fall, and indeed it is the next in order, for the root of the tree being taken away, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to the body &amp; the branches too, but death and withering? and if you take away the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a building, what will bee the end but ruine and overthrow? So is it ſurely in the ſoule, for Faith is the ground of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeene, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</p>
            <p>Deſperation once prevailing upon the ſoule, hope muſt needs bee taken away, and indeed all grace, but eſpecially hope, becauſe of the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer conjunction it hath to faith, then any other grace, either hath, or can have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What doth deſperation leave a man to the thoughts of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. Nothing, and indeed ſome men ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinke they ſhall die like the brute beaſts, and there's an end; See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Something: and ſo ſuch men as have ſome knowledge of the holy Scripture, and of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life after this, and yet wanting faith in the pardon of their ſinne, are in Scripture reputed to bee but men without hope. See <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13. See alſo, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Job</hi> 8.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are the ſignes of deſperation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> I ſhall give you a few of many of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The want of all other grace; where any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall grace is in truth, there all grace is in ſome meaſure, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.16.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171649:13"/>
            <p n="2">2. No deſire of glory to come, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Immoderate care after things preſent, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. &amp; 16. See <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Want of the feare of God.</p>
            <p>In the innocency of <hi>Adam,</hi> hee had the feare of God, which if a man want, hee lies open to all manner of ſinne; an univerſall ſecuritie falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, then hee cries peace, peace, where there is none, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. and indeed the reaſon of every enormitie is, there is no feare of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fourth ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Want of Son-like ſubjection.</p>
            <p>All the other creatures which are in the world were created to be the ſervants of God, but man onely was to become his Sonne, that hee might receive the adoption of children, and the Spirit being beſtowed upon him, hee might cry Abba Father: but in the ſame fall of mankind,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hee changeth his father, and is of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the devill, yea and the works of his father hee will doe, <hi>John</hi> 8.41.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hee changeth his refuge, dependance, ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation too.</p>
            <p>See a godly man, &amp; he will ſeek to God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, truſt him, pray to him, and have his depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on him; ſo doth a wicked man to his, as you may ſee in <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.15. to the witch.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:171649:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the next ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Servile rebellion.</p>
            <p>Man ſince the fall is according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſold under ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. He doth all the drudgery of Hell, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. his throat is an open ſepulcher, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.13. and as in thoſe places where they buy ſervants and ſlaves for money, the maſters looke that they ſhould do any thing that hee commands, and they performe it: So it is betweene the devill and his vaſſals, they are taken captive of him at his will, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>laſt.</hi> Yea, as the ſervant delights to doe what hee knowes will pleaſe his maſter, ſo theſe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe ſuch things, but have pleaſure in thoſe that doe them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſixt ſinne that diſcovers a man to bee in a ſad condition now after the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Rebellion againſt God as a teacher.</p>
            <p>Of which you ſee ſuch large complaints in the firſt Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> deſpiſing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>Now whereas men may object and ſay, God is a conſuming fire, and for us there is no more comming neare to God, then combuſtible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may come neare a great fire. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.19.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord ſtoopeth to this, and therefore giveth man a miniſtery of men like himſelfe, and takes away that objection, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171649:14"/>
            <p n="2">2. How men receive it then, is to bee ſeene in holy Scripture: <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, <hi>John</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, yea Chriſt himſelfe had their ſeverall porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for men have ſeverall exceptions againſt them. Either they are no Schollers, or they uſe not the Fathers enough, or they are covetous, ſome they ſay are too ſociable, others that will not come to them they are preciſe, they want good manners. See <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. reſiſters, ſome ſay in their hearts there is no God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. and of others ſee the complaint, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.21. all day long have I ſtretched forth my hand to a rebellious and gain-ſaying people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſeventh ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Rebellion againſt God as the Creator.</p>
            <p>That whereas God made all things for his owne prayſe and glory, theſe though they know him to bee God doe not glorifie him as God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. Nay all the glory God gets amongſt theſe, hee is faine to pluck it as it were out of their throats, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.3.</p>
            <p>So much of the effects, and fearefull fruits of the fall of mankind viſible and externall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But now what uſe of all this is to be made for our practiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Many, and thoſe exceeding uſefull too, as firſt in the fall.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I learne never to bee troubled, that God hath made all things in the world to bee of a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171649:15"/>changing condition, as wife, children, riches, eſtate, peace, health, and the very meanes of grace themſelves, fleeting and uncertaine, now here, and now againe no where, I am not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at it at all that God hath done ſo, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I rejoyee in it. For if neither the world nor any thing therein bee ſtable, but all tottering, I know it is becauſe the Lord would both bottome mee and all his even upon him owne ſelfe, which I ſhall with all my heart deſire to doe, for I know whom hee loves, hee loves to the end, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.1. and the gifts and calling of God are without repentance. I hope I ſhall cleave unto him who hath promiſed never to faile nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake.</p>
            <p>And take his Sonnes wholeſome counſell, not to lay up my treaſure any where, but there where I am ſure neither ruſt, nor moth nor theefe can come.</p>
            <p>And for my grace, and finall perſeverance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I bleſſe God that it is out of my hand, for I ſhould have loſt it and all, and beene as very an unthrift as ever hee was: but now,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I am kept humble, dependant upon God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Experienced by my falls and riſings, of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane miſery, and divine mercy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſet Chriſt before mee for an eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, unto whom I flie in all my failings.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whereas Angels and men ſtood ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171649:15"/>ſhort a while in ſo excellent a condition, wee may learne that there is no hope of ſtation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Almighty hand, in what condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wee are placed; heavy things doe not tend downeward with a more ready inclination then all our ſoules do to deſtruction: It is not all to get up into this or that eſtate, but to ſtand when wee are there, and not to fall fearefully, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.10, 11. <hi>Solomons</hi> prayer may put us in minde of our practiſe, to get up into a high eſtate is not all, but to ſtand faſt in God and in the power of his might, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe wee muſt underſtand the three things in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der here to bee obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſinne of <hi>Adam:</hi> Sinne onely is a mans overthrow.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſhame of <hi>Adam:</hi> Shame followes ſinne as the ſhadow the body.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The deliverance: Onely by Chriſt is the Churches ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as <hi>Adam</hi> committed his great ſinne, even ſo doe wee all ours, rather then wee will diſpleaſe man, our ſelves, our wives, our friends, yea our luſts, ſometimes wee will baſely diſobey our God, and hazard our eternall condemnation: So <hi>Iudas, Achan, Ahab, Eſau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Corruption gets above conſcience, and ſinne groweth ſtrong by graces weakneſſe: beſides, ſometimes wee are overpowered with a temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171649:16"/>and do that on a ſuddaine which wee repent at leaſure; at all times ſomething or othergets in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place where God ſhould bee, whom wee ſhould love with all our hearts, and with all our ſoules, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22 37. And this comes to paſſe by,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Satans ſtrength in oppoſing, for wee wreſtle not with fleſh and blood, but with principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, with ſpirituall wickedneſſe in high places, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Chriſtians weakneſſe to reſiſt and to defend himſelfe in any meaſure without a great meaſure of ſtrength from the Lord; which is to bee ſeene in <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.21. <hi>Peter, Luke</hi> 22.34. <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam. Lot, Gen.</hi> 19. <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 9. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p>And out of the ſecond part which is the effect of the fall, there is ſomething to bee learned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>Adam</hi> was a loſer in the fall of both his righteouſneſſe and inherent puritie, that no man ſhall ever bee a gainer in a ſinfull courſe: it may bee gaine may bee propounded to him, both by himſelfe and others, but hee will never thrive under it; <hi>Iudas</hi> ſtands up ſtill for an example, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.3. and <hi>Ananias</hi> with <hi>Saphira Act.</hi> 5. Remember <hi>Ahab:</hi> Haſt thou killed and got poſſeſſion? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that there is much to bee loſt in ſinne at one time, at one ſtroake, in one moment,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171649:16"/>at one throw at dice, I have heard of them that have loſt great matters, venture much at a caſt; <hi>Adams</hi> loſſe is grievous in the fall, and ſo is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poore ſinners in every ſinne hee commits, <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.36.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the devils ſubtiltie may here bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and his prevaylings over a poore ſoule, hee ſhewes us the Apple, but not the curſe, the bait, but not the hooke, the ſeeming gaine, but not the certaine loſſe, the beginning, but not the end of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the nature of ſinne, Satan, and all our ſpirituall adverſaries is hence moſt plainely diſcerned, what a craft ſinne catcheth us with, what a curſe it curſeth us with, a ſpreading curſe; we read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.9.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Propagation;</item>
               <item>Imitation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And out of the third part, which is the viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the fearefulneſſe of the fall in the ſeverall characters thereof, there may be ſeene</p>
            <p>A rule for tryall and examination of every one of us, whether wee be yet in our fallen eſtate and no further.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt doe in the underſtanding of the fruites of the fall of man, even as men doe when they ſee filthy water run downe the kennell, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171649:17"/>queſtion that men aske is, from whence comes this? So will wee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whence comes all this infidelitie, deſperation, rebellion and the like in man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> From the loſſe of Gods image in the ſoule, wherein man was created; for as from the Image of God, while man bare the ſame, and the character of the Creator was lively ſtamped on him, flowed all the teſtimonies of a full and free communion with God, in Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thus; Thou haſt made him a little lower then God, and crowned him with glory and worſhip, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.5. So from the loſſe of that Image comes a ſimilitude and likeneſſe unto ſinne, Satan and all ſuch deformitie; the liker God wee are, the more good; the liker Satan, the more evill wee muſt needs bee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But is all this Image of God loſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No: A picture of ſome beautifull man, is (ſuppoſe) in ſome of your houſes, but all blotted, blemiſhed and defaced, yet ſo as that wee can tell whoſe picture it is: ſo is the Image of God in our ſoules ſomething left, but ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and blemiſhed with our ſinne, that we can ſcarcely diſcerne it, like the ruines of ſome ſtately palace, or a dead child wherein though you may eſpie the likeneſſe of the father, yet it is but a vile and rotten carcaſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are thoſe reliques which are yet left?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:171649:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. Something in the body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. More in the mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whence elſe come theſe ſad effects upon the ſoule after the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The mind is ſinfull, depraved and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, in captivity and thraldome to every luſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Wherein doth this appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thus poſitively, there is neither actuall nor potentiall knowledge of God, See <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. without knowledge the mind cannot bee good. Comparatively thus: tell them a tale, and they will underſtand, rejoyce, aſſent and beleeve, yea and remember too: but in things of God, no taſt, no ſavour at all. And the reaſon is as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rendred by God alſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That within them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.13. they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the word of God, and what wiſedome is therein them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which is in the word it ſelfe, which the naturall man doth not ſavour, neither can hee, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But whence comes this miſchiefe to man elſe after the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> His conſcience is corrupted, hee carries about with him continually a falſe witneſſſe, which gives him an ill and indirect teſtimony on all occaſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Wherein doth this appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171649:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By a due conſideration of the offices of conſcience on this manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It falſely excuſes when it informe, that to bee no ſinne which is a ſinne, and it may bee a very great one too. See <hi>Luke</hi> 18.20, 21. hee is not aſhamed to ſay (no more are many of our ignorant people) that hee had kept the commandements ever ſince hee could remember; See another, <hi>John</hi> 16.2. they that kill you will thinke (their conſcience ſo informing) that they doe God good ſervice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It falſely accuſes when it informes that to bee a ſinne which is not, as in the things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, many dare eate no fleſh in Lent, dare not but keep ſuch a holy day and the like.</p>
            <p>Some other things might bee obſerved, but I omit them; See <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.7. they thinke to bee heard (conſcience tels them ſo) for their much babling. Some thinke they fulfill the Law of God, becauſe they keepe the Lawes of men. For geſture at Sacrament, Oh how fearefull are ſome people, whether kneeling, ſitting, &amp;c. eating ſuch meat or the like! a brother or a ſiſter is not in bondage in ſuch a caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Is there then nothing left in the conſcience now after the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yes: there is ſomething left in all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and in conſcience too, as wee may ſee in <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. where God ſpeakes of naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171649:18"/>and of naturall men, whoſe conſciences yet doe accuſe or excuſe; and when God will make it his ſcourge, wee ſee how it can open his mouth and ſpeake, how it can terrifie, torment, and become intolerable, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.3. <hi>Judas</hi> for example.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whence moreover comes this to man after the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> From the ſinfulneſſe of his memory: For let a man come to Church conſtantly, ſit under the meanes of grace, heare and underſtand ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, yea and ſeeme to bee affected with them at the time of hearing, and yet of all this hee remembers nothing, nothing becomes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the reaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. The mind doth not fully conceive of things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They doe not remember, becauſe they doe not regard, wicked men are not perſwaded how excellent it is to bee as Scribes inſtructed for the kingdome of God, and to bring out of our treaſury things new and old, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.52.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whence elſe is this great miſery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans will is ſinfull: and if the blind lead the blind (that is to ſay, a blind underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding lead a more blind will) both muſt fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ditch as deep as damnation.</p>
            <p>The will is more ſinfull then all the reſt of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171649:19"/>practicall faculties, yea the cauſe of all ſinfulneſſe in them.</p>
            <p>There is in the will an actuall and potentiall inclination of it onely to evill; See <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>John.</hi> 6.44.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. How ſhall this appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By art, and labour, and induſtry, men attaine to the knowledge and practiſe of other skils and knowledge, but never to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and practiſe of Chriſtianitie, it is God there that workes the will and the deed, 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 12.13. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whence elſe comes this great miſery to fallen mankind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans affections ſince the fall, are all out of order, and thoſe if not guided are like ſtrong and unruly horſes without a bridle, or like a ſhip without an anchor in the ſtorme, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cable, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus wee read of haters of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. lovers of pleaſures more then God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4. rejoycing in a calfe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.6. grieving at, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are the uſes of this point alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> I will declare them in order, and ſo there are two generall uſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt, that if all bee thus out of frame in man, hee ſhould repent. For the time of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance God winked at, but now admoniſheth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171649:19"/>all men every where to repent, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30, 31. Light is come into the world, and if men love darkneſſe becauſe their deeds are evill, they lie under the great condemnation, <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Secondly, and ſound repentance will require of you ſound heart-humblings, expreſſed in Scripture by the pricking of the heart, together with a diligent and indefatigable inquiry after that which yet you doe not know, yet above all things ought to deſire to know, that is, what ſhall I doe to bee ſaved. See <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.31. Theſe are the generall uſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are the particular uſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Theſe: and 1. Foraſmuch as man hath loſt the Image of his God, wee learne 1. How unlike a man may bee to his father, wee ſee ſome children much derogating from the hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and religion of their parents; Scripture teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this, and our owne experience too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wee learne that the onely remedy is that which the Apoſtle ſets downe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. to gaze upon him with open face till wee bee tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the ſame Image with him from glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to glory. <hi>Moſes</hi> you know had his face ſhone by converſing with God, and ſo will our faces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond particular uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That it is a ſad thing for the mind to bee in a ſpirituall captivitie, if the heart bee not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171649:20"/>right, no helpe unleſſe from heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That wee muſt have great regard unto the language of holy Scripture, to bee renewed in the ſpirit of our mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third uſe, from the conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That man hath a conſcience; and the reaſon why it rouſes not, and flyeth in his face is not becauſe it is not, but becauſe it wakes not; a Lyon aſleepe, if hee waken once, can bite and roare, ſo will conſcience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no man can have a good conſcience, till a worke of grace bee vouchſafed him from God.</p>
            <p>And this appeares to bee a good conſcience.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When its accuſing is according to the Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When its excuſing is according to the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fourth uſe in reſpect of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That there is as well an art as an uſe of memory; many complaine that their memory is naught, now here is a helpe, the Lord gives re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for this, a preſent remedy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To love heartily the things which God ſets before us; <hi>Oh how I love thy Law! Pſal.</hi> 119.97.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171649:20"/>No man can love that which hee knowes not, nor have that which hee loves not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fifth uſe in point of will?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That the cauſe of all our miſery is the wicked will. That the cure is here, and here onely to bee diſcerned, when God gives us a will, or a mind to know him that is good, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſixt uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To know where the worke of grace is in every good and ſound Chriſtian in his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? yes ſurely, but that is not all, in his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions too, there to the life, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.20.</p>
            <p>And thus much of the firſt part of this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, <hi>viz.</hi> the fall of mankind. Now for the ſecond part, namely, his recovery by Chriſt out of that miſerable condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What purpoſe had God toward the creature in the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No purpoſe of the finall deſtruction of the creature, but the illuſtration of his owne ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.26. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22, 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. How may the mercy of God to his elect be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſidered?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thus: If hee bee compared to the Angels which fell, they had no meanes of recovery out their fallen eſtate, <hi>Iude</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If with the reprobate; they had meanes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171649:21"/>indeed, but they had no grace to uſe them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Is the eſtate of man better in the eſtate of regeneration, or of innocency?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It is better in the eſtate of regeneration ſurely; which appeares to bee ſo,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is immutable and not to bee changed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe his happineſſe, and holineſſe is greater.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the firſt part of the mercy of God to man in his recovered eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans happineſſe which is, 1. Partly in this life; 2. Partly, or rather perfectly in the life to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Wherein doth this happineſſe of man conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In the viſion of God; ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. So the naturall man ſees God in the creature. Again, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. Spirituall men never behold him but in the face of Chriſt, which viſion is operative, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In peace, pacification, and acceſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. for hee that ſees a King, a King I ſay as his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and one ready to fall upon him with an act of anger and juſtice, had rather never ſee him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In expectation, for eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive what God hath prepared for thoſe that love him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. A beleever ſees
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171649:21"/>God as the ſonne ſeeth his father providing for him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans holineſſe, wherein the principal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent is God, and the principal patient is man: for man can ſtirre no more to the working of his owne holineſſe without God, then tooles can move without a workman to doe any peece of worke, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are the conſiderations of mans holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The miracle of it; for it is no leſſe in the apprehenſion of every naturall man, <hi>John.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The meanes of it, which are to be ſeene, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The manner of it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. as God dealt with <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.9. ſo doth hee with all his people, he gives them another ſpirit, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.24.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The time of it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.3.5. Men doe as <hi>Herod</hi> did, they keepe their birth-day, but the day of our new birth and the time thereof is not regarded.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There are ſignes of it too in holy Scripture not to be neglected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans faith: which is an affiance and truſt in Chriſt Jeſus for happineſſe; and is ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to repaire what infidelity hath ruined in us.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:171649:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whereby may this be ſet forth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By this ſimilitude: A King or monarch hath many thouſands of his ſubjects rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and refuſing to performe obedience to his juſt Lawes; the King ſeeing this rebellion, purpoſeth ſo to deale in revenging of it, as not onely his juſtice, but that alſo, and eſpecially his mercy and love toward his naturall ſubjects may appeare, and therefore hee meaneth to puniſh their offence in himſelfe, by putting to death his onely ſonne, who is of his owne nature and eſſence, yea who doth raigne joyntly and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him, being partaker of his riches, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, kingdome and honour: The death of this Prince being thus decreed by the King his father, it is needfull that for the ſuffering of the courſe of Law, together with the ſentence of death, he ſhould debaſe him to the condition of a ſubject, yet retayning all the aforeſaid priviledges; ſo that there is in one perſon the condition, and as it were the nature, both of a King and of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; the one maketh that hee may bee put to death, the other maketh, that this death, though it bee but the death of one perſon, is more then a ſufficient ranſome for the offences of 10000. of his Subjects. Even ſo did our great King with the Prince of peace in the worke of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the benefit that wee reape by Chriſts death?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:171649:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. By his merit wee have perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his ſpirit wee have perfect holineſſe, here in part, hereafter in full and perfection; See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. How is the excellent faith of a Chriſtian knowne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thus: 1. It is a part of our regeneration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſubject thereof is the will of man.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The meanes of working ſet forth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It cannot bee loſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Signes of it are as many as wee have graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But how is it that faith onely hath the power of juſtifying?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That queſtion is worthy of our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith gives glory to God, takes away crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture boaſting; if for our love, holineſſe, &amp;c. wee had beene ſaved, man might have imputed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to himſelfe, but now all boaſting is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another reaſon, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. that it might bee ſure to all the ſeed, and not bee of works at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the relation betwixt faith and other graces?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It hath this qualitie to joyne us unto the Lord Jeſus, from and by whom wee come to bee partakers of the ſpirit of Chriſt, and of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171649:23"/>increaſe of all ſpirituall graces; See <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. How doth faith and juſtification bring forth holineſſe and ſanctification, eſpecially ſeeing that to mans reaſon, it is rather a motive to a wicked and diſſolute life? ſee ſuch objections, Rom.</hi> 3.7. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. From the ſenſe of the love of God, in the pardon of ſinne the heart is inflamed with an exceeding great love of God againe, which the beleever deſires to let appeare in the keeping of Gods commandements; See <hi>Job.</hi> 14.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God doth worke upon the faithfull, not as ſtocks and ſtones, but acts and moves them, and then they do worke out their ſalvation and adde grace to grace, as is to bee ſeene plainely, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Sanctitie and holineſſe is the onely and cleare evidence of a ſound faith, without and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from which it is dead. See <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.26.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Faith without the reſt of ſanctification, is not ſufficient to attaine ſalvation, for nothing ſhall bee perfect in the other world, which is not carefully begun here, and glorification is but ſanctification perfected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fourth part of the mercy of God to man in his recovered eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans hope, of which the uſe is to cure all our deſpaire: For though it bee true that God deales with his ſometimes as <hi>David</hi> did with his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171649:23"/>ſonne <hi>Abſolon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.24. to turne him aſide and not let him ſee his face, though indeed he love him dearely and doth intend to forgive him too; yet ſometimes God brings his to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve above, yea againſt hope, for faith cannot loſe his nature which is to bee the ground of things hoped for, &amp;c. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Job.</hi> 13.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the uſe of this grace in a beleeving Christian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Threefold, 1. God ſaith it is an anchor, the uſe whereof at Sea wee know well enough, namely, to hold the ſhip, that riding out the ſtorme, it may bee kept from ſplitting; ſo hope keeps the ſoule among the rocks of impatience and diſtruſt, &amp;c. See it called a helmet too, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God ſaith it is a preſervative againſt ſinne, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3. Hee that hath this hope purgeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as hee is pure; See <hi>Job</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fift part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans holy feare of God. For whereas it may bee objected, that feare ſeemes to fight with and to bee contradictory to faith and hope, even in the eſtate of regeneration more then in the eſtate of innocency, for there the eſtate was changeable, and here it is not ſo, yet it is a grace of great eſtimate and uſe, as is to ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What uſe is this grace of now in the ſtate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:171649:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. To ſhew us that a great deale of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption reſts in us now after grace and beleeving, and that wee had need not onely to bee conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the love, but reſtrained alſo with the feare of God. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.16. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.6. with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. 2. To keepe us from ſtripes, for as it is ſaid of the Lion that hee alwayes ſpares thoſe that feare and lie proſtrate before him for mercy; ſo the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Juda:</hi> Let us (ſaith the Apoſtle) labour to pleaſe God with reverence and feare: For even our God is a conſuming fire, but fire never burnes the aſhes that lie under it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28.29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſixt part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans filiall ſubjection to his God, or mans ſon-like obedience to God as a father, wherein the Lord doth for the ſonnes of men, two great and eſpeciall things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hee recovers them to the dignitie of ſonnes and heires too, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Endues them by the ſpirit of God with a diſpoſition ſanctified, and ſutable thereunto, <hi>viz.</hi> they call him father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. they love him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1. feare him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.18. imitate him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. in trouble run to him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. <hi>ult.</hi> and moſt patiently abide his chaſtiſement, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5. let him doe what hee will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſeventh part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans ſervile feare and ſubjection to God
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171649:24"/>as his ſervant, which grace the Lord gives to his, and of this the Scripture ſpeakes under a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some are ſuch ſervants as are more eminent in the Lords ſervice, like Veſſels of Gold and Silver in the great houſe; ſerving him alwayes and in every thing faithfull in all his houſe. <hi>Moſes, Noah, Daniel,</hi> were ſuch, yea and the Lord Jeſus himſelf. Behold my ſervant, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42.1. See <hi>Num.</hi> 12.8. Such <hi>Ioſuabs</hi> now as lead his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All beleevers are ſuch, they that ſerve him in any thing; I finde that Divines delight to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it by that in the Epiſtle to <hi>Philemon,</hi> Verſ. 10, 11, 12. to the 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What more doth the Lord give unto his people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Subjection unto the Lord God as to their teacher, in which the Lord doth theſe two things. 1. Himſelf teacheth all his people (though not without the miniſtery too) the wayes of God and godlineſſe, and therefore in Scripture wee read ſuch places as theſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8.10. and that excellent place in <hi>Iob</hi> 32.8. There is indeed a ſpirit in man, but the inſpiration of the Almightie giveth underſtanding. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleevers are called Diſciples, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.26. And 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.9. yee are taught of God to love one another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And hee is pleaſed ſo to indue them with a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171649:25"/>dependance upon him for inſtruction that they heare his voyce, and a ſtranger they will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.5. their hearts burne within them while hee opens the Scriptures, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.32. they beleeve what God ſaith becauſe he ſaith it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ninth part or conſideration of Gods mercy in our recovery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Mans ſubjection to God as his Creator, which is in ſeeking his glory, and living to his praiſe, whoſe hee is, and whom hee ought to ſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What did Adam praiſe God in innocency for?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> For his wiſedome, power and goodneſſe in the creation of the world, for his juſtice in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding the holineſſe of his reaſonable creatures with life and happineſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Is there any difference betweene the cauſes of prayſing God in the ſtate of innocency, and that of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation and recovery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> O yes: God hath put a new ſong into our mouths, which you ſhall read the ditty of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2, 3. and that whole Pſalme, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. for the mercy that endures for ever and ever. Yea and the place of praiſe and the perſon of praiſe too is bleſſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The people of God deſire to live in their God, and move onely to their God-ward, to bee ordered by his word and inſpired by his Spirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They deſire to winke and beleeve, bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171649:25"/>to bee ſomething or nothing, even as the Lord will. See <hi>Iob</hi> 13.15. and that remarkable ſpeech of <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.25, 26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Is there yet any more?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> One demonſtration of mercy very high, and which <hi>Adam</hi> had not in his innocency; mans ſubjection to God as to an husband. For the purpoſe of God in our recovery is not onely to tie and knit us to him as ſubjects, ſonnes, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Schollers, and creatures, but alſo as his eſpouſed wife, married unto him in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.20. which is the great myſtery of mercy, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Wherein doth this appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> A contract is made, <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k.</hi> 16.8. downry agreed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.23. a kingdome, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32. the conjunction no leſſe then that, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.5. in the incarnation of our Lord Jeſus. And as the wife expects and attaines to have more done for her then any friend, kinſman, or other whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſo the beleever may look for more love, and riches, and protection, from her Chriſt, and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            <p>And upon this ground of ſuch an eſpeciall love, two eſpeciall duties of love wee find in holy Scripture taught us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shee that is married, careth for worldly things, how ſhee may pleaſe her husband, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34. ſo ought the beleever.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:171649:26"/>
            <p n="2">2. Heare O daughter, incline thine eare, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thy people and thy fathers houſe, ſo ſhall the King have pleaſure in thy beautie, for he is the Lord thy God, and worſhip thou him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11. To renounce all and cleave faſt to God.</p>
            <p>Now for the uſes of all that hath been heard, in their order.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, wee may learne that ſweet leſſon from hence; that in the fall of mankind, the Lords intent was not deſtructive, but that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in man might ſee himſelf and ſeek his God offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which is indeed the proper end of Gods deſertion and caſtigation of all his owne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee learne that there is a reſt, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, renovation, regeneration, for the Lords people, which the election doe obtaine, and all the reſt are hardned, as is to ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that this recovery, out of the ſnare of the Devill, (wherein till then we are taken cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive at his will, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26.) it is in order and according to all the parts of the fall, leſt that the medicine ſhould bee ſhorter then the diſeaſe, and the ſalve not ſutable to the ſore.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that all the meanes of grace, <hi>viz.</hi> preaching, hearing, reading, prayer, reproofe, &amp;c. are all intended by God, and ſhould ſo bee by man, to recover us out of our fallen eſtate.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that whoſoever will thrive under the meanes of grace muſt onely uſe them to that end
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171649:26"/>unto which God hath appointed it and alle which is onely his glory and the ſalvation of mankind.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, that for as much as the ſpeculative or knowing onely of any thing is not that which is or can bee uſefull, that therefore our recovery graces bee known of us in experience and practiſe.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, and that ſuch a thing is eaſie to bee done to him that will underſtand and bee dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, the queſtion and anſwer following doth make plaine.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall I know whether I am recovered to any eſtate of happineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> See the particulars in the part, Happineſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Doſt thou deſcrie a God cleerly in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? the workman in the worke?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doſt thou ſee him more clearly in his own Image the Lord Jeſus?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Haſt thou perſwaſion of thy peace, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propinquation of drawing nigh?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then thou art happy and mayſt expect from God with comfort, that which eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, neither hath entred into the heart of man to conceive; and ſo of holineſſe and all the other parts in order.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall I know whether I have attained to any meaſure of holineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> See the particulars in that part, Holineſſe.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:171649:27"/>
            <p>Was that mercy a miracle to thee? doſt thou remember the time (with joy of heart) when God wrought it? haſt thou any evidence, ſigne, ſeale thereof? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.13. and ſo of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Now as the Jewes once asked of our Saviour, Whence hath this man this learning, &amp;c. So will wee alſo of a Chriſtian recovered out of the fruits of <hi>Adams</hi> fall,</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whence are all theſe parts of his recovery? out of what fountaine were theſe ſtreames derived?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In our Saviours owne language, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.23. If the eye (that is, the mind of man) have light in it (that is, bee illuminate from God) it doth enlighten the whole body, but if it bee darke, there is nothing but darkneſſe in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: that is in ſumme, as is the eye ſeeing to the body to guide and governe it in actions, ſo is the mind inlightning to all the parts and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule, to governe it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whence comes all our obedience unto, beleeving in, and dependance upon God in the eſtate of our reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very from the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From that, becauſe our minds being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, wee know our God to bee juſt, holy, and good and mercifull, &amp;c. and therefore doe performe acts of love, feare and obedience to him: For as the ſubjects of a King doe therefore love and feare him, becauſe they know him to be grea
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171649:27"/>and good, ſo doe the ſubjects of the great King alſo.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>By what ſignes or otherwiſe do wee diſcerne this mind-inlightning?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thus; 1. It is the firſt worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation or recovery, as is to ſee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.23, 24. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9. Light in the creation was the firſt worke, ſo in the redemption it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is the moſt apparent and convincing te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of regeneration, either to our ſelves or to others that can be in the world, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. dull, rude, unlearned, and ignorant men to bee by Gods holy ſpirit inlightned and made to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and live in the great myſtery of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea to diſcerne all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. as our Saviour ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> Fleſh and blood never revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this to thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.17. So ſay I, this is no work of nature, but from our Father which is in heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is yet but in part onely in this life, for wee ſee now through a glaſſe darkly, but then wee ſhall ſee face to face, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond thing or part in our recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whereby our deliveranee from the fall is made cleare and viſible to us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The conſcience amended and renewed in both the parts or offices thereof, that is to ſay, both accuſing us, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.40. then <hi>Davids</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:171649:28"/>heart ſmote him; and excuſing us alſo now after our recovery, 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 3.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>How may this bee opened unto us now that it may bee plaine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thus: 1. Every faithfull man hath true knowledge of ſinne by the renewing of his mind, and alſo ſinne it ſelfe by the infirmitie of the fleſh, and therefore they have an accuſing conſcience, heart-ſmitings, weeping bitterly for ſinne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering their wayes, and acknowledgments, ſuch as that of <hi>David,</hi> I have done very fooliſhly, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>Hence ariſe in the moſt faithfull; 1. Feare of temporall puniſhments. 2. A great increaſe and daily practiſe of ſelf humbling, ſelf judging and condemnation: And 3. This is a reſtraint to the godly to keepe them from ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The faithfull have an excuſing conſcience alſo, which doth excuſe them before God; and this muſt bee thus underſtood.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The conſcience doth excuſe them in regard of their owne inherent righteouſneſſe, not as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perfectly holy, but as being ſincere and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained: ſee <hi>David</hi> often, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The conſcience doth excuſe them alſo in regard of the imputed righteouſneſſe of Chriſt unto the beleever, for hee is made unto us of the Father, wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. and in him yee are compleat, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:171649:28"/>
            <p n="3">3. This excuſing conſcience hath two eſpeciall things to bee marked therein.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that it dare not looke upon the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of Gods juſtice, for then it would bee but as a filthy clout; and indeed none excuſer dare peepe in here but Chriſts righteouſneſſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but flies to the court of mercy, and love, and to a throne of grace to find helpe in, at a time of need, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that here hence ariſeth to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ones all their triumphant perſwaſions of Gods love, their ſalvation, and a full and finall victory over ſinne, hell, death and judgement, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. It is God that juſtifieth, who ſhall condemne? and who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the third part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A ſanctified memory, which may be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Scripture ſaith of ſuch people, that they do ponder &amp; lay up in their hearts: the word would bee obſerved (lay up) in their hearts, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.51. For as hee that layeth up a thing for his uſe, when occaſion is to uſe it, can go and fetch it out again: So faithfull men bring out of their treaſury things new and old, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.52. See more to this purpoſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.35. and ſee the practiſe of <hi>David</hi> what a peece of experience hee brings forth laid up long before, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.34.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:171649:29"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Scripture ſaith of ſuch men, that they lay up truth in their hearts, the holy Scripture which is the fountaine, and ſuch choice ſtreames as that, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. Remember that Jeſus Chriſt of the ſeed of <hi>David</hi> was crucified according to my Goſpel. And the Scripture diſcovers the purpoſe of Gods people in ſo doing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.11. I have hid thy promiſe in my heart that I might not ſinne againſt thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The way and meanes which Gods people uſe to lay up theſe things, <hi>viz.</hi> hearing, reading, remembring, comparing the Scriptures together, applying them to our daily uſe and whetting them upon our families, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the fourth part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A renewed will, ſeene in one man in the holy Scripture, in two remarkable circumſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What a monſter the will is, bent in violent perſecution againſt God and godlineſſe untill the Lord renew it: the inſtance is <hi>Saul, Acts</hi> 9.1, 2. breathing out ſlaughter, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What a miracle of mercy God can and doth ſometimes worke upon ſuch a ſinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By what things may I know whether my will bee renewed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Holineſſe and the things of God will bee made naturall to thee as it were, thou wilt walke in the Spirit, a godly man though indeed good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may bee contrary to his corrupted nature,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171649:29"/>yet to his regenerate part it is very ſutable, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22, 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth, the will of a regenerate man doth I mean, actually incline it ſelfe to that which is good (though imperfectly and impurely) and that becauſe it is ſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It cannot totally and finally decline what is good, though a beleever may fall and that foully, yet he will recover, there is a principle of heaven, the holy Spirit, and fire from God, which cannot but aſcend, and be active, yea reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe till it come to his owne place. See 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.19.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the fifth part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Excellent affections, ſuch as love, hatred, &amp;c. In which regeneration keepeth his Court, Throne and eſpeciall reſidence. For as a ſhip without ſailes or wind muſt lie ſtill, not ſtirre and be becalmed, ſo Religion, Faith is dead without works, and it is the labour of love (above all) which will bee rewarded, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherein may this be opened?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In this. 1. God-love is in the regenerate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the commandement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37. with all the all in ſome meaſure; 2. Man-love is in them too, good-man love, by this they are known to bee Chriſts Diſciples, becauſe they love one another, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.35. See alſo 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.3. Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, that is, a renewed love to himſelfe, that is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:171649:30"/>the better part of himſelf, his ſoule, in the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> things, <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.36.</p>
            <p>Yea and to them that are neer him and in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him for ſoule ſervice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the contrary alſo, as 1. Devill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatred and reſiſtance. See <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. So ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. &amp;c. 2. Man-hatred: Do not I hate them that hate thee? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.21. 3. Selfe-hatred, that is, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> naturall, ſinfull, yea and ſpirituall ſelfe too, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, our beſt workes, if ſeeking to ſtand in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with or to dethrone the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Some uſe of all this muſt bee remembred, and ſo wee have done with the two things propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to bee handled in this Catechiſme, <hi>viz.</hi> Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> recovery out of his ſinfull and loſt condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the ſeverall uſes of this doctrine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The 1. that there is a recovery for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God: Devils have no meanes, and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates no grace to uſe any though they have them, but to you it is given, as our Saviour ſaid to his Diſciples, to know the myſteries of the kingdom of God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. If thou haſt taſted, praiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy God, O praiſe him, in his Sabbaths, in his Sacraments, remember him and think of this, <hi>Can.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.13.14.</p>
            <p>The 2. that this recovery of ours is no work
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:171649:30"/>of nature, (do not ſleep your ſelves into deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) but of grace, a mightie worke of grace, wrought by God, at a time whereof no man (that ever taſted) was ignorant, but knowes, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers it, and admires God in it, yea and can ſay, I was a blaſphemer, &amp;c. but God had mercy on me: ſo 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The 3. that it is not of yeſterday, to have men 1. thinke carnally and groſſely of the work of our regeneration, ſo did <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> otherwiſe a great Scholler, and a man in great place and preferment too: alas it is not that ſends a man to heaven the faſter, nay it's well if it do not ſend him the faſter to deſtruction, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yea and ſcoffe and ſcorne at it too, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Atheiſts now adayes do, ſo did the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie men, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.18. for theſe men were great traders in learning, but had dealt for no grace at all, which is the condition of all ſuch (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they thinke of themſelves) which are ſuch as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And therefore to underſtand and not to be led by any thing in the world as example, but to take courage, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.14. yea and to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience too of hearing the Shepheards voice and not following a ſtranger. See <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.5.</p>
            <p>The 4. is, that thou tell others, (when thou art converted ſtrengthen thy brethren) when thou art recovered, O ſeeke to pull others out of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:171649:31"/>the pit) O you can tell others the fearefull eſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the feareleſſe and ſecure carnall man, that he that cries Peace, peace, where there's no peace, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> certaine (if not ſudden) deſtruction is comming and the Lord will not bee mercifull to ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one: ſee 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19.</p>
            <p>You can tell them the comfort and joy tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you had in beleeving, the ſweet felicitie in a comfortable walking with God, and the more happineſſe which is in the conquering one ſinne then in committing a thouſand; you can diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to them the fare which Chriſtians have a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their fathers table, even the wine and the milke in the garden of grace, to which the beloved of God are invited, <hi>Can.</hi> 5.1. whereof whoſoever eateth and drinketh ſhall never hunger and thirſt more, and whoſoever taſteth not thereof, hee may feed deliciouſly every day here, but the time commeth (and God onely knoweth how ſoone) when hee ſhall not have (no though hee had a heart to aske it, which is impoſſible) a drop of cold water to coole his tongue, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>The 5. is, that hee that deſires to know his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eſtate, doe examine, prove, and try him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by the aforegoing evidences, after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and as is before directed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How ſhall I knew that I am in the eſtate of recovery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thus, 1. Is the eye open to the mind? and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171649:31"/>doth it doe that ſame office to thy ſoule which the eye doth unto the body, <hi>viz.</hi> keep in the way and out of the ditch, in obedience and out of ſinne, in the way of God, out of the way of the devill?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why doth a Chriſtian love, feare, truſt God, but becauſe hee knowes the juſtice, mercy, &amp;c. in our God? And they that know thy name will put their truſt in thee, for thou Lord haſt not failed them that ſeek thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The firſt principle in the world before the Spirit of God moved thereon, was darkneſſe, darkneſſe moved upon the face of the deepe; ſo is it in worldly men, all is darkneſſe, they love darkneſſe, they doe the deeds of darkneſſe, and their reward will bee the blackneſſe of darkneſſe, if God do not give them light.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And for the convincing of our ſelves &amp; others of the worke of grace throughly, doe as the poore blind man did, draw thy argument ſo, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.25. One thing I know, that I was blind and now I ſee: ſo I would have every one of us doe and ſay, I was in wofull miſery and hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved me: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. and ſo of the reſt of the particulars.</p>
            <p>Of the fall of mankind and his recovery, thus much bee ſpoken, now let us to the third point, which is the gratious meanes whereby this reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very may through Gods bleſſing bee obtained,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171649:32"/>that is to ſay, the Word and the Sacraments of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Whether all the Word of God be neceſſary to bee preached to the elect of God before, in and after their actuall converſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes ſurely, and if he be an approved work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which handles the ſame, not without an eſpeciall benefit with Gods bleſſing. The Law, for by it comes the knowledge of ſinne: ſo the Apoſtle, I had not knowne ſinne but by the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. And the Law is our Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to bring us to Chriſt. Thus the other Lawes, as the ceremoniall and the judiciall, are uſefull too, for they ſerve to ſhew ſinne, though not directly, yet by accident, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. This was the courſe of old amongſt the Preachers of the Goſpel; <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.13. and ſo it muſt be now.</p>
            <p>Before wee preach promiſes, wee muſt preach threatnings.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Law is reſembled to the ſeed, the Goſpel to the fruit, and the preaching to the breaking up of the fallow grounds, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>The Law is like the needle which pricks and enters to bring after the thread which cloſeth the feame, rent or breach.</p>
            <p>And as for preaching the Law, and exact obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereunto, even after juſtification of Gods people, it muſt not be omitted, for it is the rule
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171649:32"/>of life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.195. hath both its coactive and directive force upon beleevers: It is perpetuall, becauſe morall; laſteth in the Church Militant to them, to whom through Gods mercy the commandement is not grievous, 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 5.3. For they deſire not better teſtimony of their love to Chriſt than the keeping of his commandements, <hi>John</hi> 14.15. It laſteth in heaven the Church triumphant, for obedience ſhall there continue; and why ſhould wee thinke the Law, which is the rule thereof, ſhall there bee aboliſhed? Many excellent and indeed extaticall admirations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of read all over the 119. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder what conſederation is the Word of God when it is the meanes unto the ſalvation of our ſoules?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It muſt be preached. For though the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Word of God hath its particular and private, and indeed excellent uſe to them that make conſcience thereof, yet preaching is the ordinance of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the thing which you call preaching?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. You may take the Apoſtles deſcription of his owne paines thus, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.26, 27. I am pure from the blood of all men, for I have kept no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing back, but have ſhewed you all the counſell of God. The Ambaſſadours duty is to deliver the mind and will of his Maſter that ſends him, ſo is it the duty of the preacher, Gods Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.20.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:171649:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is required of him that is a Preacher of the Goſpell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Foure eſpeciall things; the firſt is the right dividing of the Word of God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. a twofold ſimilitude there is in that one word, one taken from the cutting of bread for children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom if wee ſet the whole loafe they will riſe hungry, or it is taken from the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans cutting and lopping off the ſuperfluous branches. See <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.45. and <hi>John</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is a diſtinction betwixt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and the vile, the cleane and uncleane, a diſtinction betweene Sheep and Goates, ſuch a skill as the Lord complaines of the Shepheards of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for want of: See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.1, 2.17.</p>
            <p>The third is a holy courage, boldneſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in the things of God, and the worke of God, and wayes of God: ſee <hi>Jerem.</hi> 1.17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>The fourth is an holy ability for conſolation and ſatisfaction: wee muſt bee like the Oracle of heaven, like our Maſter, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.1. not break a bruiſed Reed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.20. to ſtrengthen the weake, to heale the ſicke, to bind up the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to bring againe that which was driven out of the way, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is required of him that is a hearer of the Goſpel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Two things. 1. Attention, which is the applying of the underſtanding to perceive the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171649:33"/>will of God. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14. God opened, and then ſhee attended. It is in Scripture called the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after God, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58.2. A wiſedome goes, or at leaſt ſhould goe along with it to know and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the good will of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. yea and if the Lord pleaſe to worke this in us, then wee conſult not with fleſh and blood, but with him and his truth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Intention, which is the applying of our will to the will of the Lord our God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.106. this is called in Scripture obeying from the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. and in regard of this the Law is ſaid to be in the heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8. Such a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſhould be in the hearer, as <hi>Jerem.</hi> 42.5, 6.</p>
            <p>There are foure reſemblances unto which the hearers of the Goſpel are likened:
<list>
                  <item>1. To a Sponge.</item>
                  <item>2. To a Water pot.</item>
                  <item>3. To a Strainer.</item>
                  <item>4. To a Sieve.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are the workes of God upon his elect in hearing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Very many, but foure eſpecially:
<list>
                  <item>1. The heart opening, ſo <hi>Lydia, Act.</hi> 16.14.</item>
                  <item>2. The heart pricking, ſo <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37.</item>
                  <item>3. The taking away the vaile, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.</item>
                  <item>4. The teaching of God, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are the dealings of God toward the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:171649:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In the hearing of the Word of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, thus it fares with the reprobate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They heare, but underſtand not; ſee, but doe not perceive, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 6.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God deſcribes the hearing of the Goſpel by the foure grounds, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Stumbling at the Word of the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fore-ordained thereunto, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Is there not ſome particular and peculiar work which God doth upon his people in hearing more then on other men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yes, and it is that of which God ſpeakes, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.33. the inſcription and writing of his Law in our hearts, which work is indeed no other thing but the very finger of God ingraving in the heart as in a table, his Law and our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What are the effects of ordinance uſing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Many, ſuch as theſe: Joy in beleeving, In whom 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. after, &amp;c. yee rejoyced; it is ſet forth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.44. The Eunuch went on his way rejoycing, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.39. And there are two both infallible and indeed inſeparable compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons joyned together, namely ſanctification of the Spirit, and beleefe of the truth, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>Now for the uſe of this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the firſt uſe of this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:171649:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> An information in the true, ſober and evangelicall uſe of the Law of God, which is that before, and in, and after converſion it bee preached unto Gods people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond uſe of this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> An information, that preaching is the ſoule-ſaving ordinance, the faith-begetting meanes ordinarily, as is to ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. Whence theſe two concluſions follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the chiefe buſineſſe of that day, which is ſet apart for the ſoule to bee wrought upon, I mean the Sabbath day, is preaching, that is the work of the day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the reaſon why few of our people at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to meaſures and good degrees of grace, faith, and godlineſſe, is their deſpiſing of the meanes, neglect, or loathing, or contempt of ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: this is complained of <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> An information when the miniſter is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged and the people may be truly ſaid to die in their ſin. The canon is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.19.</p>
            <p>Men that are wicked having once been warned, and of the wrath to come, and do not come in to God nor repent, muſt die unpitied and unla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fourth uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The Preachers dutie, divided into parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, the Preachers looking-glaſſe, wherein
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171649:35"/>he may ſee the rule of right preaching, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Evangelicall loafe amongſt the Churches children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fifth uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The hearers direction, O you that deſire to heare with profit, and to do your ſouls ſome advantage in an holy ordinance, looke to your guidance, take your direction with you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Underſtanding, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Will muſt be both preſent, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſixt uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Tryall of that great thing; the maine queſtion is here decided whether the Lord deale with me as an elect one, or as a reprobate one under the meanes of grace; ſee the tryall here plainly ſet forth unto you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Doth the Lord open my heart, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth he paſſe by my ſpirit, &amp;c. And ſo of the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſeventh uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The 1. Prayer of a Chriſtian for heart-inſcribing, that the Lord would pleaſe with his owne finger to write.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Practiſe of a Chriſtian, to obſerve our Lords direction in hearing him, that is, Chriſt Jeſus the great Prophet. Wayting on the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of grace. Depending on the word for all of a Chriſtian, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the laſt uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:171649:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Proofe of Soul-rejoycings have wee any at all? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5. What and whence they ariſe, <hi>Luk</hi> 10.20. Joy in heaven for the converſion of a ſinner. From heaven for, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.4, 5, 6. a place worth the remembring.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt meanes, the word of God; now for the ſecond meanes which is the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Do wee read of ſuch a word in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> No: nevertheleſſe wee read of ſomething that is of equall ſignification, that is to ſay, a Signe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. a Seale, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. it is called a Myſtery too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But what is a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> An outward and viſible ſigne, of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; ſpirituall grace, ſo plainly, and in that language. In which deſcription I ſhall look upon theſe particulars: 1. The ſigne, and there we ſhall ſpeak of the ſignes that are Sacramentall, and of them it will be very needfull to know,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in reſpect of the thing ſignified a ſigne is either of things paſt, and then it is called commemorative, that is, a ſigne wherein ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing paſt is remembred; or of things preſent, and then it is called demonſtrative, that is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſomething preſent is ſhewed forth; or of things to come, and then it is called prenuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:171649:36"/>that is, foretelling ſome things to come; or elſe a ſigne is that, that ſhewes forth all theſe, or at leaſt partly things paſt, and partly preſent, and partly to come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That theſe ſignes in the Sacrament do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſerve the underſtanding, and then they are called ſhewing ſignes; or the memory, and then they are called warning ſignes; or the faith, and then they are called ſealing ſignes; or of theſe, all three together; and this is that which is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be known concerning ſignes.</p>
            <p>Thus of the ſigne. Now 2. of the word (outward.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What meanes that by ſaying outward and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That which may bee ſeene by the bodily eye, and in this place the queſtion is concerning the ſignes in the Sacrament of what force and power they are: In which I find the opinion of former times to bee threefold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſaid and taught that the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſignes did conferre grace, now this by no meanes is to bee admitted for the reaſon expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed afterwards.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they give to the ſignes that which is to be given to God alone, and then the people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not what God, and what the ſignes doe ſeverally performe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they give all unto man in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171649:36"/>of grace, and nothing to Chriſt; and from thence ariſes the Prieſts forgiveneſſe of ſin, the tyranny &amp; lording it over mens conſciences, and that deſperate point of denying heaven to the Infants that die without baptiſme: a great deale of theſe dregs doe yet reſt and ſtay amongſt our people, that in the very ſigne, there is ſome more then ordinary holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſpake of the ſignes <hi>diſpoſitively,</hi> that is to ſay, that ſignes were inſtituted of God, not onely to ſignifie grace but to diſpoſe it, and ſo they ſay that whoſoever was baptized, and did receive confirmation, did beare the badge and character of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another opinion they had whereby all was taken from the ſignes, and they reputed to bee no more then other things in a profane uſe.</p>
            <p>For the right underſtanding therefore of the doctrine of theſe outward ſignes; the truth is, the ſignes do offer, but in their owne nature they do not conferre grace; they are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace, for God hath inſtituted them, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and of themſelves they doe not, indeed they cannot give it.</p>
            <p>For concluſion then of this point, obſerve theſe things or conſiderations following, that is to ſay:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is onely of God to give that which theſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171649:37"/>ſignes do repreſent and ſhew forth: ſo <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43 25. I am hee which blot out thine iniquity, and <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By a neceſſitie of the meanes, the ſignes are helpfull, and not to be neglected, no more then the looking up to the brazen Serpent, of that Iſraelite which would have cure, but the Spirit blowes where it liſteth, <hi>John</hi> 3.8. By grace yee are ſaved, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Scripture ſpeakes plainely, that grace is given before the receiving of the ſigne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. and after alſo, as is to ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 2. and 8. and 10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Inſtances are given which cleare it, and put it out of queſtion, that many have received the ſignes without ever receiving grace, it was the caſe of <hi>Simon Magus, Act.</hi> 8.23. <hi>John</hi> 13.27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Thus of the ſecond part, the word (outward) ſigne; Now of the third part which is grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is that thing which you call the grace or the inward grace of the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here we ſhall ſee the difference now between a Sacrament and a teſtament; all the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is indeed Gods teſtament, but the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the Seale of the Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Now in this Teſtament of God, there were two Covenants, unto which the Lord did ſet the Seales or the Sacraments, as is to ſee in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:171649:37"/>
            <p n="1">1. In the Old Teſtament there was a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of workes, which ran thus with <hi>Adam,</hi> As long as thou continueſt holy in obeying my word, thou ſhalt ſo long continue happy in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying my preſence; And to this Teſtament or Covenant there were two Seales put, the tree of life, which was the Sacrament of their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, if they perſiſted in their obedience to God; and the tree of the knowledge of good and evill, which was the Sacrament of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or of their tryall rather, whether they would abſtaine from eating of the forbidden fruit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In both Old and New Teſtament, there is one Covenant of Grace, which runs thus, What the Law could not doe in as much as it was weake through the fleſh, God did, by ſending his owne Sonne in the ſimilitude of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſinne condemned ſinne in the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3, 4. That the righteouſneſſe of the Law might bee fulfilled in us, and that whoſoever beleeveth in him might not periſh but have everlaſting life; See <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.33.34. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.13. <hi>John</hi> 3.16, 17, 18.</p>
            <p>Now unto this Covenant, God ſets his two Seales, the white Seale of Baptiſme, and the red Seale of the Lords Supper. And thereby doth aſcertaine every faithfull man and woman (uſing the Sacrament rightly &amp; faithfully) that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171649:38"/>of grace in Chriſt, and all the benefits which are promiſed therein doe not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the whole Church, and all the faithfull in generall, but unto them and their ſoules in particuler; And not onely ſo, but,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They uſing the Sacrament according to divine inſtitution, do hope for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And do alſo profeſſe themſelves bounden by that Sacrament to ſhew forth all poſſible ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of life before God, his holy Angels and all good men. See <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10, 11. See alſo <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74.75.</p>
            <p>And to draw to the concluſion of this point alſo, corcerning this Teſtament and Sacrament, or Covenant and the Seales thereof, let theſe things following be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Sacraments of the Covenant of Grace, are onely inſtituted for the faithfull; for as it is ſaid of the Word of God, that it profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not them (of whom the Apoſtle ſpeakes) becauſe it was not mixed with faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. in thoſe that heard it: So it muſt bee ſaid and thought of the Sacrament alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That therefore the moſt excellent things of God, may and do (in ſome caſes) loſe their power of profiting the ſoule. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.25. Thy circumciſion is made uncircumciſion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.26. not a penny difference between thee and a heathen in the heart. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. three notable places.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:171649:38"/>
            <p n="3">3. That likewiſe the profit reaped and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit gotten out of the Sacraments is not by the worke done, as the Papiſts ſay, and too many of our people thinke, but another way ſurely.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That one and the ſame thing is given to, and received by the faithfull both in the Word and Sacrament, namely Chriſt with all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits; no difference in the thing, that is all one, nor in the manner of receiving, for that is all one, namely by faith, onely the difference is in the outward forme, for in the word preached God onely deales with the eare, but in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments with the eares and eyes too, for hee addeth Signes and Seales to them.</p>
            <p>So wee have done with the third part, which is the Grace of the Sacrament. Now of the fourth part, inward and ſpirituall grace, or inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Why is this grace called inward?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It is ſo called (amongſt other) for theſe two Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With reſpect unto the Signe, for that is but meerely externall and altogether outward, is received with an outward part, the mouth, digeſted with an outward part, the ſtomach, and gives nouriſhment onely to the outward man, the body; but the other is received with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward act, to wit Faith, and yeelds ſpirituall nouriſhment to the inner man, in which reſpect
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:171649:39"/>it is called Meat indeed, and Drinke indeed, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.55. and the Manna and it ſweetly compared together, 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.49.50.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With reſpect unto the Seat, for this hath place in the heart, and ſoule, and inner man; See <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9. Beleeve with the heart, called the heart-anſwer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.7. and the anſwer of a good conſcience, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. not the waſhing away the filth of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Why is it called ſpirituall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> From the qualitie of it, for the more of grace any thing hath in it, the more ſpirituall it is; which may bee ſhewed by that ſpeech of <hi>Ioſhna</hi> to the people, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.19. Yee cannot ſerve the Lord, for hee is an holy God, hee is a jealous God, &amp;c. what is the meaning? yee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerve him, 1. as you ought; 2. as hee will accept, unleſſe you bee very ſpirituall and leave your idolatry. See <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.24.</p>
            <p>The quantity of it, for grace fits the Spirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the greateſt ſervices, and fills it with all abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances and ſatisfaction therein too, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Why is it called inviſible?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It is ſo called; 1. In regard of others, the eye of man cannot ſee the proviſion, that God hath made for his, both in grace and glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. the perſwaſion, the ſatisfaction, the heart-rayſings, and ſoule-quicknings, which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:171649:39"/>God in an ordinance or Sacrament feeds and fils his people with which the world ſees not; as our Lord ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 4.32. I have meat you know not of, ſo can the Chriſtian too ſay to the world and to every unbeleever, There's meat for me in the word and Sacrament which you know not of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is called inviſible in regard of us too, for the time was, when the very beleever came blindfold to the Sacrament. We were darkneſſe, though wee bee now light in the Lord, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. And it is by faith onely that wee ſee inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27.</p>
            <p>Some uſes muſt bee made of this point, and firſt of the firſt part in order; wherein theſe two things in order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To learne, what a Signe, any Signe, but eſpecially a Signe in the Sacrament is; <hi>viz.</hi> a thing inſtituted by God in that holy buſineſſe of our ſoules, unto that end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I might ſee what things God intends by it to put mee in mind of in the Sacrament, which are the things paſt, thoſe are Chriſts death and ſuffering, and ſatisfaction for me and the ſinnes of all the elect.</p>
            <p>The things preſent, thoſe are, the grace of perſwaſion and obſignation, or ſealing that all theſe belong to mee, I being a beleever and rightly uſing the Sacrament.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:171649:40"/>
            <p>The things to come; namely, that I ſhall in glory have a full, and free com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him there for ever, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.35.40.58.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That I might alſo ſee what parts of my ſoule, or faculties thereof theſe Signes in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament ſerve to benefit whilſt I am receiving and after: that is to ſay;</p>
            <p n="1">1. As they ſhew mee any thing, and ſo they ſerve to my underſtanding; for when I ſee thoſe Sacramentall actions of breaking bread and powring out of wine, I am put in mind of the breaking of the body and the powring out of the blood of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they doe warne mee of any thing, and ſo they doe ſerve my memory; for in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Sacrament I am put into remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to bee thankfull for and to preſerve the remembrance of the death of my Saviour untill hee come, as one friend gives another a booke or a peece of gold.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As they ſeale any thing, and ſo they doe ſerve my faith; for as I doe receive bread and wine into my body with which I am ſecretly, yet certainly nouriſhed and grow up to the things of a man, ſo I doe beleeve that I have and ſhall receive the Lord Jeſus into my ſoule, that holding the head, whereof all the body is knit together, and having nouriſhment mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171649:40"/>I may increaſe with the increaſes of God, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p>Thus of the firſt part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What uſes are to bee made of the ſecond part, that is to ſay, of the doctrine of the Signes in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> They are ſweetly uſefull to a diſcerning receiver.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To try his obedience whether hee will with reverence uſe them, in obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the great God, and with a heart ſo diſpoſed that if the Lord had bidden ſome grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thing hee would have done it, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To try a Chriſtians wiſedome, for hee hath more of heavenly grace and direction in him then to depend upon any thing under God for that which hee knoweth muſt onely come from God, for it is God that worketh the will and the deed, 2 <hi>Phil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It ſerves greatly to make a man fitted for his acknowledgments of the Lord; for if the Spirit blow where, when, and on whom it liſteth, then it is not of him that runneth nor of him that willeth, but of God that ſheweth mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. And ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. laſt verſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It puts a Chriſtian into a trembling poſture all the time of receiving to remember <hi>Iudas</hi> his ſop, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.27. and <hi>Magus</hi> his Baptiſme, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.23.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:171649:41"/>
            <p>Thus of the ſecond part, Signe outward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the uſe of the third part, which is the Grace of the holy Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It ſerves for many ſweet purpoſes: as for example.</p>
            <p>In that the firſt Covenant of workes could not ſave, I learne to remember the miſery of man: Oh woe unto us for ever if wee were put to our own deſert at the hands of God!</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Covenant of Grace I learne to remember the exceeding great, &amp; bottomleſſe, yea indeed boundleſſe mercy of God, who when we were loſt was pleaſed to recover us againe in the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>For the Sacraments I do deſire to eſteeme them no otherwiſe then the Seale of the Teſtament of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And therefore think my ſelfe bounden unto theſe things following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The moſt ſober and ſanctified uſe of them that poſſibly I may or can, that God bee not provoked to curſe that to me which to others is a bleſſing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That I am ſtrictly tied by them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme my ſervice in all poſſible holineſſe to God, as ever I deſire to receive from him the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments benefit. For otherwiſe,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhew that I have none of Chriſts Spirit, and if ſo, then I am none of his, that's moſt cleare, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:171649:41"/>
            <p>Secondly, I deny the end, fruit and purpoſe of the grace of the Goſpel, which is ſet downe clearely, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I deny that power to be in the fleſh and blood for ſpirituall nouriſhment, which is in bread and wine for corporall growth and ſtrength.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That I underſtand that this bread was and is appointed for the children to bee food for them, dogs muſt not eate it, and therefore muſt look that I can cry <hi>Abba</hi> father, if ever I mean to be received into Gods favour or family. See, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.22, &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I am to know that to the unclean all things are uncleane, yea even the very conſciences are defiled, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</p>
            <p>So for the uſes of the third part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What uſes now are to bee made of the fourth part, that the grace of the Sacrament is called inward, ſpirituall, and inward?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Theſe in order. 1. That God in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things, hath and indeed deſireth to have to doe with hearts, ſoules, and inſides, whoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, pardoning and the like, God doth and indeed wee ſhould in theſe holy things chiefely aime at. See to this purpoſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 16.22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That a man had need to bee very ſpirituall in the drawing nigh to God, were it for no other
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171649:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:171649:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:171649:43"/>reaſon than this, that the benefit is a ſpirituall benefit, aad indeed the naturall man doth not perceive, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. old men muſt have ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, all men muſt have grace, and the Spirit of God, which doe either perceive or receive bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in a Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Faith of a beleeving Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant is a certain wonderfull kind of Grace that can pierce into the ſecret of ſalvation, and bee able to ſee the hidden things of God.</p>
            <p>No wonder carnall men care ſo little for the beſt things of God, they are on the dark ſide of them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.20.</p>
            <p>No wonder beleevers are ſo affected with them on the other ſide, for the Goſpel is the power of God to ſalvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the generall conſideration of a Sacrament, yet more clearly and wee goe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to aske,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Who is the author of a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> God onely, who did inſtitute and ordaine the Sacraments both in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and unto them annexed the promiſes of grace and glory, which was in the power neither of man nor Angel to performe.</p>
            <p>And therefore the holy Sacraments are by the Miniſters of God onely to bee adminiſtred, and of theſe alſo as in the name and ſtead of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Why cannot man be the author of a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:171649:43"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Beſide that one great reaſon aforenamed, there are two more to bee obſerved; the 1. Man giveth, hee can give neither promiſe nor reward to any ſervice; the 2. God will not bee ſerved according to mans appointment, but as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhall ſet downe and determine, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29.29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the matter of a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It is a point of doctrine and divine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that concerning which the learned have diſcovered themſelves divers wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They have ſaid that the matter of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is twofold, one in the ſenſible and terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſigne, another in that thing or truth, which is by the ſaid ſigne ſet forth and ſignified unto us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thus they have taught, that the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall element, as water in Baptiſme, and bread and wine in the Lords Supper, that is the matter, (yet not without ſome higher thing therein, and thereby ſet forth and ſignified as was ſaid before) of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Which ſaid Matter, though it be corporall, yet it is alſo ſpirituall, as is to ſee, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3, 4. ſpirituall I ſay, not in regard of the ſubſtance, for that is not all changed, but in regard of the end; upon which a wiſe receiver is to looke with this fourefold conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the bread and wine is not now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171649:44"/>and common, but holy, that is to ſay, by God ordained and inſtituted to a holy and ſpirituall uſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is the inſtrument of the holy Ghoſt, by which he is ſpiritually efficacious in the heart of the beleevers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That by them the ſpirituall good things, are both ſignified, given, yea and ſealed up to the beleevers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That to a wiſe receiver theſe things doe not ſo much ſerve to the body as to the ſoule, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. They have called the matter by a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is to ſay, the earthly matter, and the heavenly matter, meaning the ſigne, and the thing ſignified, and therefore they taught that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooved thoſe which came unto the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to thinke that there they ſhould receive two things, to wit, an earthly thing after an earthly manner, that is, bread and wine with the mouth of the body, and a heavenly thing after an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly manner, that is, Chriſt Jeſus by faith.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. If you ſhall ſay briefely, Chriſt is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Sacrament, it is ſound doctrine, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is uſefull for theſe two purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To try all falſe and ſpurious Sacraments, for ſuch they are all where hee is not found to bee the matter: by which rule if five of the Popes ſeven Sacraments be tryed, they will be found too light.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:171649:44"/>
            <p n="2">2. To try all true receivers, for thou mayſt receive the matter of the Sacrament and yet not receive the matter, the bread of the Lord, and not the bread the Lord, the outward but not the inward matter.</p>
            <p>In a word, when Chriſt did deliver to his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples the bread, and ſaid, This is my body, and when wee in his ſtead doe the like to you, it is ſuch a ſpeech as if a Prince ſhould when hee had given one a faire Mannour, bring him the Grant or Letters patents thereof, and ſay unto him, <hi>Loe there's your Mannour, &amp;c.</hi> Which ſerves for the underſtanding of the words wee ſpeake to you in the delivery of the matter of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the forme of the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Of this alſo you ſhall heare what was taught of old; 1. They ſaid that the forme of the Sacrament were thoſe rites, ceremonies or uſages in the Sacrament, which were agreeable to Gods Word, and ſo to primitive inſtitution. Hence that aſſertion is amongſt the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that the word of God is the forme and ſoule of a Sacrament: from which two things were concluded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the words of our Lord in the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought onely to bee uſed, without any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or diminution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And that therefore it ought ſo to be done,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171649:45"/>becauſe every receiver ought ſo to receive as if the Lord Chriſt himſelfe were preſent to give the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they did diſtinguiſh of the forme of the Sacrament, and truely taught that this forme of the holy Sacrament was twofold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the manners of adminiſtring the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, that is to ſay, thoſe rites and orders which were agreeable to our Lords inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, which they truely called the outward forme of the Sacrament: Therefore the Apoſtle deſiring to ſhew the <hi>Corinthians</hi> how the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought to bee adminiſtred, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24, 25. repeateth the words of our Saviour onely.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſweet analogie, ſimilitude and reſemblance betweene the ſigne and the thing ſignified. As for example.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Wherein is this fitneſſe in bread to ſignifie and ſet forth Chriſts body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> See this: 1. The bread is broken.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The bread nouriſheth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The bread ſtrengthens. So,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The wine is poured.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The wine reviveth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The wine makes glad. So,</p>
            <p>The Lord was broken and his blood ſhed, that hee might nouriſh and revive, yea that hee might ſtrengthen and make glad the drooping conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and ſad hearts of ſuch whoſe conſciences
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:171649:45"/>are preſſed with ſinnes guilt and feare of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation all their life long, and this is the inward forme of the Sacrament. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, one thing more they noted worthy of our obſervation, which is, that the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the elements was either, 1. Conſtitutive, that is, that which is ſet downe and appointed of God, to bee the words of the ſame, ſo thoſe words, This is my body, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Invocative, that is, ſuch as is to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the prayers of all the Congregation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which in Scripture is called bleſſing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. and ſee that place, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is then the forme of the Sacrament wee have ſeene, but now tell us onely the end of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Of that much muſt bee ſaid, for as it is very true that the end of a thing &amp; the good of that thing are ſo convertible, that untill the end and uſe of a thing appeare, there is no benefit of that thing to mee: So is it in the Sacrament ſurely, for by the cleare underſtanding of the Sacraments ends, we ſhall as clearely ſee the end and uſe of the Sacrament alſo, wherein is the benefit of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What then are the many and maine ends of the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Theſe following, that is to ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it may be a monument, Signe and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171649:46"/>Seale of the Covenant of Grace and of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt in all the benefits of our ſalvation which are given already, or are hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to bee given to the Church.</p>
            <p>So the Paſſeover was a remembrance not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their deliverance paſt, that is to ſay, out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but alſo of the future deliverance which they were alſo to have in, by, and through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And our Paſſeover is a ſweet memoriall not onely of the redemption of Chriſt made upon the Croſſe, but alſo of that which is to bee perfected when Chriſt ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead, and fully to deliver his people from ſinne and death, and all the enemies of their ſalvation, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.35.40.50.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it may bee a warning to us of that obligation wherein wee ſtand bound to become the people of God by covenant and agreement. This is like the boaring of the eare under the Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Sacrament is the bond of mutuall charity, concord, and love betweene the Church and people of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Sacrament is as it were the very ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of our publike meetings, and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the worke of the Miniſtery, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe badges do diſtinguiſh the people of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171649:46"/>God from all heathen and ſtrangers; the Church of God is diſtinguiſhed from unbeleevers, and idolaters, ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.43. No ſtranger ſhall eat thereof.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The end of the Sacrament is, that thoſe of the houſhold may eat thereof, and no other. Men prepare their meat for their ſervants, and for their family. So God, <hi>Lev.</hi> 7.20. And all the family come together and expect their meat from their maſter, or from him who is by the Maſter appointed to give them their meat in due ſeaſon, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.45. So the Sacrament in the conſtant and conſcionable uſe thereof doth diſcover us to bee of the ſociety of the Saints and family of the faithfull.</p>
            <p n="7">7. God doth intend hereby that wee ſhould in the reverent and ſober uſe of this ordinance give others occaſion to inquire and learne what it is, and ſo bring them to bee acquainted with the wayes of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <p>Nor for the uſes in order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the firſt uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That if God bee the author of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; 1. Wee labour to ſee God in the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, and ſo with reverence behave our ſelves both in hearing and receiving. The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to come with <hi>Pauls</hi> authority, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. the people with <hi>Iacobs</hi> behaviour, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.16. And no man to goe out from the holy things
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:171649:47"/>as hee came in, but bettered either in judgement or affection, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 46.9.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that wee labour to ſtirre up the gift of Faith and our dependence upon God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. for hee is faithfull that hath promiſed, and all the promiſes are yea and amen, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. wee deſire to truſt ſolvent men for great matters, ſo to beleeve the truth-performing God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that wee may and ought to expect Gods power from, &amp; his preſence in the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Gods Sun, when it ſhines it doth heat and enlighten all the creatures below: ſo to ſee whether Gods Sacrament and the Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe doth ſhine upon, heat, qualifie, and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our cold, earthly and frozen hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That if Chriſt be the matter of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then; Firſt, wee labour to take heed to the Sacraments which we receive, and indeed to the word wee heare; for no preaching where Chriſt is not preached, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. No Sacraments where Chriſt is not received; and therefore the ſervants of God muſt learne to refuſe all other Sacraments beſides the two onely.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee learne that hee muſt needs bee a happy man that receives the Sacrament aright, for hee receives the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. Yee have received not the ſpirit of bondage to feare againe, but the ſpirit of adoption; Yee
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:171649:47"/>are Chriſts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22, 23. and that one place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. how ſhall he not with him give us all things?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that wee have an eye upon two eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialls; 1. The preparation, or that which is the Inſtrument of our receiving Chriſt, namely faith, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. and therefore deſire the Lord to ſhew us the impediment of our comforts in the holy things, ſee <hi>Mark</hi> 9.23, 24. that wee may behave ourſelves humbly under all our wants and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The perſwaſion, fruit, benefit, advantage, accrewing to the ſoule out of the Chriſt-giving ordinance, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. what power, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.12. contentation and acquieſcence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That if the forme of the Sacrament bee the Word of God,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They doe well that have regard unto the ſure word of propheſie as unto a light ſhining in a darke place, ſee 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. For in vaine hee worſhips God, that brings for doctrines the traditions of men; and as in all other things, ſo in this eſpecially, me thinkes the Lord ſhould appoint the rule of his owne worſhip; ſo then wee learne to take up <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution, I will hearken what God ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If wee would bee prevailed withall to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our ſelves, from the forme of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:171649:48"/>wee might learne to try whether there bee that union between the Sacrament and us, which is between the ſigne and the thing ſignified: the bread is broken, ſo Chriſt, but for mee? <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. the bread nouriſheth, ſo doth Chriſt my ſoule? The bread doth ſtrengthen, ſo doth the Lord Jeſus mee? yea <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.12. I can doe all things through Chriſt ſtrengthening mee; and ſo of the reſt, hee that will make conſcience of examination of himſelf and ſelf-judging thus, ſhall doubtleſſe find the comfort of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wee learne that when wee come to a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, it is our dutie not to ſit ſenſeleſſely there, or gazing after this or that vanity, as too many doe, but to helpe with your prayers mightily that the Sacrament may be effectuall and very powerfull. You complaine of ineffectuall &amp; live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ordinances, you are in fault, you bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed and liveleſſe ſoules; the word of God would run and bee glorified, if you would like brethren pray for us. See 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.1. You muſt helpe to conſecrate and ſet an edge upon the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, the element, the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Whereby may a Chriſtian doe this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thus: 1. The capacity of a Chriſtian muſt bee looked unto. Art thou a beleever? a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert a Chriſtian. You force us to lay the plaiſter upon a dead mans ſore, if you come to the Sacrament in your unbeleefe; Wicked men come
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:171649:48"/>to the Church, to the Sacrament, but the Church, the Sacrament, never comes to them: ſuch places as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. and <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The care of a Chriſtian muſt bee regarded, his care I ſay to do at a Sacrament time with his ſoule as <hi>David</hi> doth in a time of praiſe with his ſoule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.8. Lord awaken my faith, love, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, zeale, meditation, judgement, all: gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will bee aſleepe, the devill buſie, deſertion it may bee appearing, to ſtirre up therefore the gift of God, blow up the fire, and ſeeke new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration to every new action. Our beſt duties, alas, are for the moſt part worſt performed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fourth uſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> That if there bee ſo many excellent ends of the Sacrament, wee labour earneſtly, 1. To bee informed that there ought to bee no reſt in a Chriſtian heart, untill wee ſee ſome of theſe ends in our hearts, lives, and ſpirits, appearing evidently both for our comfort and others good example: the end of eating, the end of ſtudying, the end of trading, gaine, nouriſhment, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, theſe are thoſe wee looke at in naturall things, and ſuch ſhould bee our care alſo in things ſpirituall. See <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſee two names wee read of old given to the Sacrament which I intreat may bee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was called an Euchariſt or a worke of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:171649:49"/>thankfulneſſe anſwerable to that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. Do this in remembrance of mee: and ſo a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould thinke when he is called to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; Oh I am called moſt thankfully to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him that forgot not mee when I was in my low eſtate; the God that delivers the Church from all her ſinnes, how much more from all her ſorrowes? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.8. and to ſay of the Lord Jeſus as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of his Church, If I forget thee, let my right hand forget her cunning, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was called a Love-feaſt, and ſo they that were called to the Sacrament did uſe to give ſomething to the poore, that ſo they might te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie how that by the uſe of the Lords Supper, they were oblieged to performe works of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to the poore according to that of <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.10. and ſo a Chriſtian ſhould think, I am cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led now to remember the members of his body who is the head of the Church, and what I doe to them hee will account to bee done as unto him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. A cup of cold water given to a Diſciple in the name of a Diſciple ſhall not loſe his reward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But what more particular uſes are to bee made out of the ends of the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In a word, all the uſes of the ends of the holy Sacrament may bee well reduced to theſe following particulars, that is to ſay:</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:171649:49"/>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of Chriſt, and there is a worke of commemoration to be done, &amp; that is to fill our hearts with the remembrance of him, the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of whom filleth all things. Neither can this bee done without thankſgiving, if ever wee have taſted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of our ſelves, and there is a worke of tryall and ſtrict ſearch, what confirmation, nouriſhment, pacification, wee get; <hi>Luke</hi> 24.32. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.51, 52. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In regard of others, and ſo there is a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold dutie that wee are to deſire to bee exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in, and to make others witneſſes of.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the offering of our ſelves; and all that wee have to him which hath offered himſelfe to death for us, to deny our ſelves, and all that wee have for Chriſt, which is a duty every where preſſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the acknowledgment of our ſelves to belong to the company of the faithfull, in and under theſe badges of our profeſſion, and ſo to bee ready to render a reaſon of the hope that is in us with meekneſſe and feare, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. Not forſaking the aſſemblies, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the fellow-feeling of the miſeries of our brethren, to bee like affectioned, to beare one anothers burden, and if one miſery befall one member that the reſt ſympathize.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Are there not ſome caſes of conſcience
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:171649:50"/>
               <hi>to which a Communicant ought to have an eſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard in theſe Sacrament duties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> There are very many, but I ſhall onely commend theſe two unto you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How often a religious Chriſtian ought to make conſcience of receiving? Very often; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly much might bee ſaid in this point: The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeemes to leave it to the diſcretion and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the wiſe beleever.</p>
            <p>The primitive Church uſed it very often.</p>
            <p>In the times of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. it ſeemes they did it every time they met: Some have followed the old courſe of ſuperſtition and determined, three or foure times a yeere, at leaſt it ought to bee done, and that for ſuch reaſons as theſe following, that is to ſay:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe thankſgiving is comely, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 33.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, our Saviours words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee owe to our faith and aſſurance, care of increaſing them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. for this cauſe many are weak, &amp;c. Out of which it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred that if God puniſh a wrong uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, hee will alſo not beare with a rare uſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus have men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aught concerning this caſe of conſcience.</p>
            <p>Something more I ſhall intreat to warne you of in this point for the true knowledge of this
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:171649:50"/>how often wee ought to receive.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To tie a people at ſuch times, at ſet times to receive the Sacrament, is both ſuperſtitious and abſurd; men were wont to bee excommunicated if they did not receive, but never queſtioned if they were not fit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All men are not to receive it alike often, the ſtrong Chriſtian may and ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive oftner then the weake, his ſenſes are exerciſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. But there is feare that the other may eate doubting, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The obligations are very binding for often receiving, where men are fit and qualified, as God to have his praiſe, our ſoules their peace, quickning, rayſing, &amp;c. and our profeſſion its ornament, with our brethrens example and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable reſpect.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The dictate of a mans owne ſpirit, I ſay of a beleevers owne ſpirit, will bee beſt for this point, to whom I ſay as in another caſe was ſaid to <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.7. When theſe ſignes ſhall come unto thee, doe as occaſion ſerves, for God is with thee. Marke the dictate of thine owne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>The ſecond caſe is, how worthily a religious Chriſtian ought to receive the holy Sacrament?</p>
            <p>To this point exceeding much ought to bee bee ſaid, and I will ſay ſomething.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is not indifferent whether a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:171649:51"/>well or ill, I ſay it is not indifferent or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not in reſpect of God, for 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27. his preſcript.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not in reſpect of man, for 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. his profit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the Scripture ſeemes to include it all within the compaſſe of that dutie of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and tryall; ſo that hee which knowes what belongs to that dutie of examination, and practically falleth upon the ſervice of ſelf-tryall, ſeemes to performe the whole worke of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is then the duty of examination of tryall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In it I ſhall obſerve theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There muſt bee knowledge preſuppoſed, and ſo idiots are not at all fit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There muſt bee will to amend too, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to what purpoſe is examination?</p>
            <p n="3">3. An exact rule for tryall, otherwiſe is not any thing to bee tryed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Such a tryall as God will have, and the things, to be tryed will beare.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Reaſon of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What kind of knowledge is required of them which come to the duty of examination and tryall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> This will bee beſt underſtood by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what the Scripture ſaith of knowledge,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:171649:51"/>which is ſaid to bee either naturall knowledge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14.15. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 28.26. or it is legall knowledge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. or Evangelicall, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. which is called elſewhere ſpirituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9. Now all theſe three kinds of knowledge are neceſſary unto examination. By the firſt a man ſhall ſee that there is a God, and that hee ought to bee ſerved; by the ſecond a man ſhall ſee how farre hee hath been from the ſerving of God aright; by the third hee ſhall ſee the onely way to bring him into the ſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: for this is eternall life, to know God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt whom hee hath ſent, <hi>John</hi> 17.3. and ſee <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.13. So that unto true tryall and examination, a threefold know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is neceſſary as you ſee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Why all this knowledge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> For great reaſon: as firſt, our way of teaching, for it is poſſible to convince nature out of her owne principles, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Lawes vindication, that it is a rule of life, according to which the tryall muſt bee both for preſent and futurity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Goſpels dignitie, that when all meanes of ſafetie failed, then Gods love in Chriſt ſhone brightly.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the juſtifying of an old rule in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, this it is, The worſhip of God is from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the manner of worſhip is from the Law,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:171649:52"/>but the virtue and power is all from Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What diſtinct things am I to looke upon, and ſet before mee in the duty of my examination and tryall, before and at the Sacrament in way of knowledge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Theſe in particular, that is to ſay:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Miſery, which is either generall, in the fall of mankind, and conſiſteth in ſinne and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thoſe two inſeparable companions, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7. and is ſeene daily in the propagation and imitation of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Or elſe ſpeciall miſery, and our owne perſonall ſad eſtate, which is ſeene in the commiſſion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable evils, in the omiſſion of innumerable goods, which might have been done to others, and received from them, with the juſt vengeance of an Almighty God due againſt theſe things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Redreſſe thereof, either by juſtification, where wee are to ſee how wee have behaved our ſelves toward the whole doctrine of the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of our ſoules out of our ſinne and the curſe; and ſo <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. <hi>John</hi> 15.22.</p>
            <p>Or elſe by ſanctification, where wee are to ſee how farre ſhort wee come of either being able to doe or willing to ſuffer according to the will, how unable to pray to God, or praiſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Are there not ſome choyce Scriptures to be read, at or before the time of receiving, which would bee uſefull to a willing Chriſtian in this caſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> For the doctrine of miſery read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:171649:52"/>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. or <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. The doctrine of Mercy read, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53. <hi>John</hi> 17. and 18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. The doctrine of purity read, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. and 13. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> all the Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Now if ſuch kind of knowledge be required in examination,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Oh the great condemnation which lies upon our people! and why? <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Oh the great lamentation! here is required ſo much knowledge, and I bring with me ſo much ignorance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An exhortation, Oh ſeeke, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.2. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 34.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A direction, 1. To your duty. 2. To your danger, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.1.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond thing which is ſuppoſed in examination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> A will to be amended, otherwiſe, to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian we goe, becauſe we would have cure, there we draw our purſes, no coſt is ſpared. See <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.8.</p>
            <p>Without a cordiall intention of cutting off right hands, &amp;c. no right examination; As God ſaid of <hi>Coniah, Jer.</hi> 22.24. So ſhould wee ſay of our ſinnes; as <hi>Saul</hi> of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.44. So muſt hee that examines doe and ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſinne, if the neereſt or deereſt, I will part with it, that God may not part from me.</p>
            <p>Here alſo this point will put us into a ſad condition; do not wee draw neere with our
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:171649:53"/>lips while our hearts are farre from God? Doe not wee doe thus with our ſinnes? Confeſſe them to day, and commit them to morrow?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. See the companions of godly ſorrow, and take heed to your ſelves in this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What other thing is it fit wee ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in this doctrine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Theſe following, that is to ſay:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Divines helpe us with this diſtribution; ſome ſinnes are in the will, but not of the will, that is to ſay, originall ſinne; ſome are in the will and from the will, ſo are the ſinnes of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate men; ſome ſinnes againe are partly from the will, and partly againſt it; ſo are the ſinnes of all regenerate men; And this laſt they expreſſe by a ſimilitude thus, as the Merchant in the ſtorme caſts his goods into the Sea, partly with his will and partly againſt it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They diſtinguiſh of the will of man and ſay, that there is a deſire, or a wiſh and a will, of which ſee, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.4. <hi>vult et, &amp;c.</hi> Many deſire amendment, with lazie and heartleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The denomination of a Chriſtian is and ought to bee from the better part, as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a Blackmore is not called white becauſe his teeth are ſo.</p>
            <p>A ſhield which is white on the one ſide and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:171649:53"/>black on the other, cannot bee called black or white properly, but partly black and partly white.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Wherefore ſerve theſe diſtributions, diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſimilitudes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> They are excellent for the dutie of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination and triall, which is the buſineſſe in hand; For hereby,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Men may ſee how ſinne is of their wills and in their wills, which is worth the obſervation, See <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Men may ſee the difference between, wiſhing for grace, and willing of it with induſtry, paines, abſtaining from appearance of evill, and the like.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we ought to call and account of men as God doth, with charitie, and yet care and conſcience too, not calling good evill, or evill good, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10 3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Beſides, a weake Chriſtian ought not to bee diſcomforted, becauſe of little. God gives thee a name from that little, becauſe it is the better, part <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third thing ſuppoſed in examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> A rule for to try a thing if it bee metall preſuppoſeth a touchſtone, if moiſt a meaſure, as pint, quart, pottle; weights are tryall for ſome things you know, God throwes men into the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:171649:54"/>ballances and finds them too light, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.27. Now here wee muſt agree to two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Scripture is the onely tryall, the alone rule, to try men by, to try I ſay, men, matters, and every thing by in the Church of God: this is plaine, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.19. ſee the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of a rule.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe I would confirme this and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it out of the hands of Papiſts, ſee theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The teſtimony of God dependeth not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the witneſſe of man, but the Scripture is the teſtimony of God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.9. therefore needeth not man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which the authority of Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon ought to be before it ſurely, but the Church is after the Scripture.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Scripture hath the properties of a rule for tryall, which are theſe; 1 independent, 2 ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, 3 plaine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that all the Scripture is ſo, that is to ſay, both the Law and the Goſpel, both the old and the new teſtament. There is diſtinction and difference in holy Scripture, it is true, thus, In reſpect of time revealing, ſo it is called the old and new Scripture.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of authority proving, ſo the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall and the Apocrypha.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of matter handling, ſo the Law and the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:171649:54"/>
            <p>It is true that the Law hath his office and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and place, as the Goſpel hath his yea, and even thoſe Lawes which now under the time of the Goſpel, ſeeme to be uſeleſſe, as the Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and Judiciall, do ſerve excellently to ſhew ſin by accident.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Doth the Scripture ſpeake diſtinctly of any rule for examination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It doth, as for example:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In things materiall or corporall, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.13. there it is a rule, a line, a red thread, a direction without which you know, they cannot worke.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In things doctrinall, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.15. there it is the meaſure, and whatſoever is not agreeable to it is out of ſquare.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In things practicall, and there it is the path, the road way, Gods high-way for his people to walke in, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. and herein they find a lanterne bee it never ſo dark, for Gods word is ſuch, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. Why ought wee to bee ſo carefull of a rule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> For many, and indeed thoſe are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great reaſons; as for inſtance, theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The comfort of it; it is ſweet to a Chriſtian to think, I have in my tryals looked to that rule by which I am ſure the Lord will try mee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The conſcience of it, it is the evidence of ſincerity to a beleever, yea and his perſwaſion too that hee ſhall not bee confounded while hee
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:171649:55"/>hath reſpect unto all Gods Commandements <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hereby wee reconcile the Law and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, eſtabliſhing the Law by Faith; ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hereby wee take hold of thoſe hornes of the Altar for ſure refuge, mercy and truth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the rule &amp; the refuge, the Law and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and deſire to make our wayes like Gods waves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fourth thing ſuppoſed to bee in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Such a tryall as God will have, and the things to bee tryed will beare, for both theſe muſt bee regarded in our examination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the former of theſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Such a tryall as God will have is this. 1. That wee may try our ſelves, not other men, that wee ſuſpect, examine, judge and proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our owne ſpirits, which the Scripture commends unto us as a dutie, ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a danger, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.41.42.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That wee try and proceed againſt that of our ſelves which wee know God will bee ſure to try and proceed againſt, that is to ſay, all of our ſelves, our words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.37. our workes, our thoughts, <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.14. for ſuch a tryall God will have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the latter of theſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:171649:55"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Such a tryall as the things to bee tryed, will bee able to undergoe and beare, that is to ſay, a legall tryall and evangelicall.</p>
            <p>For the further clearing of this point, wee muſt know that Divines doe helpe us with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a tryall of things perfect, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are not made to bee better, but found to bee what they are, with which kind of tryall man is ſaid to try the Lord, and his word too, See <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10. Prove mee now and try mee, if I will not poure you out a bleſſing without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: By this tryall if a man fall to try the Lord, hee ſhall find him what hee hath declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee; ſee the ſame place, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. So if a man try Gods Word, he ſhall find it to bee the power of God, &amp;c. ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. &amp;c. ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is another tryall, whereby things imperfect are ſo tryed, that they are found to bee evill, fraile, faulty and ſinfull, and are made better and in time come to bee perfected: with which kind of tryall God and his Word doe and ſhould try men, yea and with this tryall man ſhould try himſelf alſo, ſee <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.3. The Lord ſhall fine the ſonnes of <hi>Levi</hi> as Gold and Silver, that they may bring offerings to the Lord in righteouſneſſe, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p>From this diſtinction therefore I ſhall draw
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:171649:56"/>for you theſe concluſions. 1. That no man ought to bee diſcouraged becauſe new tryalls find out and doe diſcover new corruptions; for this is Gods purpoſe, and ſhould bee mans pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to marke miſery and move toward mercy, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That our perfection in this preſent world is to ſpy out our imperfections, that is our glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That no man is or ought to bee exempted from tryall before the Sacrament and an exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but hee that is quite free from any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which either God, or his Word or Spirit can find out.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That if ever there were Myſtery and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy interwoven and ſweetly knit together, it is here; God brings a man to owne his ſinne, and then ownes him, for hee came not to ſave the righteous, but to call ſinners to repentance, <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.31. &amp;c. The whole need not the Phyſitian, but the ſicke: under the notion of a ſorrowing ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſinner, wee draw neereſt to a ſupplying, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring Saviour.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That wee may ſee the uſe of both theſe try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als ſweetly in the Sacraments. 1. God will try thee there, and hee ſhall find thee, alas, an unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, unbeleeving. <hi>Job</hi> 42.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou wilt try God there, and thou ſhalt finde him (if thou wilt but caſt all thy care upon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:171649:56"/>him) no leſſe then ever he was to any: Come to him I charge thee, and preſſe him with that prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.132. No leſſe then ever hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to bee to thee and ſuch as thou art. Come therefore with thoſe words of <hi>Paul</hi> in thy mouth, O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver mee from this body of ſinne! (which by tryall I have found out) Oh I thanke God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23, 24. ſee alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fift part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Even the reaſon of all this, which may be gathered out of all that which is before delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſomething more added thereunto, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That the knowledge of a Chriſtian may bee compleat, his knowledge of things I ſay which are of ſoule-concernment. See how the men of God beare themſelves upon their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Iob</hi> 19.25. I know that my Redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, &amp;c. And I know whom I have beleeved, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. A right man in his receiving ought to bee like old <hi>Iacob</hi> in his bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.19. I know well my Son, I know well, and therefore not to bee diverted. I require you therefore to ſee that your knowledge in the holy Sacrament bee, 1. ſpeculative, diſcerning and direct, which is in theſe three things following in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Every thing in the Sacrament to bee taken
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:171649:57"/>after his owne kind and nature, that is to ſay, figurative ſpeeches, figuratively, and others other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: as for example; This is my-body, that is, the figure of my body; no more. Againe, this bread is now no common bread, but by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, an Euchariſt or Sacrament; no leſſe: For as wax ſtamped with the Seale of a King, differeth not in ſubſtance from other wax, and yet in value is much more excellent, and may not bee unreverently handled without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the King, ſo is this bread, and ſo the wine in the holy Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sacrament to bee uſed of us according to Chriſts holy inſtitution, that is to ſay, as hee commanded, and ſo onely without either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting, or altering, or adding or any thing. And ſo Popery will bee overthrowne, 1. Which gives the bread without the cup, and 2. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe which deſires bread and cup too. without due preparation and promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. No other ends propounded in receiving but thoſe of God, which are:</p>
            <p n="1">1. A due commemoration of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A true communication of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And this ought to bee our direct knowledge, without which no right receiving.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A practicall and reflect knowledge, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is a knowledge together with
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:171649:57"/>God, for if our heart condemne us not, then have wee boldneſſe with God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.21. the triple teſtimony to bee ſealed up unto a beleever, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.8. the ſpirit, and the water, and the blood, to goe ſealed from the Sacrament like thoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.3. before the hurt come upon the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is this ſealing of a Chriſtian? for of this the Scripture ſpeakes diverſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The Scripture ſpeakes of a Seale, which is the fore-knowledge of God concerning the ſafe cuſtody of thoſe that bee his, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. and againe, it ſpeakes of a Scale which is the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualneſſe of the miniſtery in the converſion of men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.</p>
            <p>To Seale, which is to eſtabliſh civilly, ſo <hi>Eſter</hi> 3.12. which is to eſtabliſh ſpiritually, ſo <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. which is to take a deep impreſſion, <hi>Can.</hi> 8.6.</p>
            <p>The Seale which is that earneſt of our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and of Gods Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. which is not as a pawne or pledge that may bee taken up againe, but part of payment, binding the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine between our God and us, and making them to bee the ſure mercies of <hi>David, Eſa.</hi> 55.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What then is that which is to bee learned from hence for our practiſe in the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt, I learne to examine my perſwaſion of comfort in my ſafe cuſtody, my ſoules reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:171649:58"/>for an everlaſting God dependance.</p>
            <p>My converſion alſo in the effectuall co-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word of God, and the Spirit of God, and the Sacrament of God.</p>
            <p>Mine eſtabliſhment, ſo that heart-triumphings do ariſe out of the ſame. I know whom I have beleeved, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. And I am perſwaded that nothing ſhall ſeparate betweene mee and the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. The deep impreſſion which this hath taken and ought to take in my heart, and all them that ever taſted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2.</p>
            <p>The certainty, (becauſe I have received part of payment of Gods unchangeable love towards me) for whom hee loveth, hee loveth to the end, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.1. and the gifts and calling of God are without repentance.</p>
            <p>So much for the firſt reaſon of examination, that there bee knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the ſecond reaſon of our examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Will to bee amended, whether the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver bring with him a ſted faſt purpoſe of amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whatſoever ſhall be found to be amiſſe upon our examination.</p>
            <p>The great queſtion between God and man in holy Scripture is that, if not onely, yet in a great part ſurely, when man comes to God that is his queſtion, If thou wilt thou canſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.2.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:171649:58"/>when God comes to man that is his queſtion too, Wilt thou bee made whole? <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.6. So then in an ordinance wee muſt looke at and pray for this concurrence; namely 1. The Lord to bee willing to doe for us; for it is not of him that runneth nor of him that willeth, but of God that ſheweth mercy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our ſelves to bee willing to ſuffer the word of exhortation, the worke of ſanctification, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For theſe two things are ever to bee obſerved in holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the hinderance of our holineſſe and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, which God ſaith is ever in the will; See <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the helpe which is onely in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God our Lord, for it is God that worketh in thee both the will and the deed, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. even of his good pleaſure: In which I deſire may bee obſerved, that Grace is the work of God, therefore there can bee no power of reſiſtence; And Grace is alſo the work of man, therefore there can bee no ſhadow of violence.</p>
            <p>Againe, to worke with a danger of not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to paſſe agrees not with the power of God, whoſe will is not will, unleſſe it bee omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that is to ſay, unleſſe it worke whatſoever it will.</p>
            <p>To worke by conſtraint and compulſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees not with the nature of man, whoſe will is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:171649:59"/>not will, unleſſe it wills what it worketh; ſo then this is all for the concluſion, Lord let Grace in mee bee thy work, then I am ſure there can bee no reſiſtance, and let it bee my work too, then I am ſure there can be no violence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the third reaſon of our examination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> His acknowledgment of Gods Word, (which ought to bee in every Chriſtian) for the rule of tryall, for the rule of life, for the rule of obedience alſo; and indeed there are but two things which Scripture preſents us with.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A ſure rule, which is the Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſure refuge, which is the Goſpell; concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both which, ſee one excellent place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. Curſed is every one that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth not in all things which are written in the book of the Law to do them; here is the corra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the Law, but then Verſ. 13. Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, when he was made a curſe for us; there is the comfort of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the reaſon that ſuch regard muſt bee had to a rule in our examination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> This, 1. our ſubmiſſion and caſting down, ſo comes the knowledge of ſinne and the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us all unto our kees before God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our certaintie, for wee are not left to try our ſelves by cuſtome, example, Lawes of man, opinion of others, &amp;c. but the never failing truth of God.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:171649:59"/>
            <p n="3">3. Our ſatisfaction, for herein wee finde a ſure word of propheſie; yea indeed that which will make the man of God compleat, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Scripture is declared to bee that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious antidote or preſervative by which Gods people are kept from the pathes of the deſtroyer.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All men are ſent unto the Word of God for their tryall and amendment: Wherewithall ſhall a young man amend his way, but by taking heed thereto according to thy Word? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the fourth and laſt reaſon of our exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It is twofold, firſt, drawne from God; hee will have a tryall, and ſuch a tryall as hee will have: for our God lookes both to the matter and to the manner of all his peoples performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as is to ſee every where, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58.</p>
            <p>Now in every tryall that God requires of his people, there are theſe things ſuppoſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Deteſtation of ſinne, for herehence ariſes all our in quiry after ſinne, its purſuite, judging, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, condemnation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Amendment of ſinne, which indeed is and ought to bee firſt in the intention, ſo <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.59. conſideration and turning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Approbation of our ſelves, both unto God, and to the rule alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. a reſpect to God and to his Commandements.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:171649:60"/>
            <p n="4">4. Example of our brethren too, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1, 2 they which obey not the Word, may without the Word bee wonne if they many behold your meek converſation coupled with feare.</p>
            <p>Second reaſon is drawne from the things themſelves which are to bee tryed, which can be no other but either good or bad, perfect or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and therefore muſt come within the compaſſe of thoſe two things which the rule will exactly helpe us unto, that is to ſay;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Juſtification; if ſo bee thou beeſt good, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and preparing onely (with an honeſt heart) though not prepared, the weeping faith-wanter may come neere to Chriſt, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.24. Men have ſaid ſomewhat of themſelves, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. I have fought, &amp;c. I have deſired to try, judge, confeſſe, condemne, from hence-forth there is mercy for mee with a mercifull God; and God deſires that his ſervants may goe from ſome of their duties with a Well done good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Condemnation, which is and cannot but bee the portion of all ignorant, unbeleeving, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examining receivers; for as counterfeit Gold may goe for true, till the touchſtone come, and then it is diſcerned, and rejected too, ſo it is here in the Word, there is the touchſtone, ballances, weight, meaſure, furnace and all for all, which (will they, nill they) ſhall thereby be examined.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:171649:60"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. What is the condemnation under which unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiving falleth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It lyeth under, 1. The condemnation of Gods Word, for as long as all the Scripture is Gods Word, and ſome particular places are not blotted out, the raſh and unprepared muſt needs bee concluded guilty, as it is to ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. &amp;c. 29. this condemnation receiving unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lies alwayes under.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The condemnation of Gods people, for all thoſe, as well the people, as the Paſtors come trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blingly and truely, and thereby condemne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and raſhneſſe; examples are pregnant, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.3. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. Scriptures very plaine as before.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The condemnation of conſcience ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it lies under, ſurely (it would alwayes if conſcience were awake) mens hearts tell them that they are not fit for ſuch holy myſteries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. How do men uſually behave themſelves under ſuch condemnation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Some ignorantly and affectedly, ſo 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 28.15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. Some careleſſely, and deſperately, ſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. Some contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictorily and ſcoffingly, ſo <hi>Act.</hi> 13.45. Some are convinced but relapſingly, ſo 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. Some mournefully, and beleevingly, ſo which as ſoone as they beleeve, <hi>Act.</hi> 12. and inquiringly, ſo <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. and ſuccesfully, ſo <hi>Act.</hi> 16.33, 34.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
